<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true art of liuing well The right vse of things indifferent. The plaine foot-path to the paradise of God. Three sermons preached at Cambridge, Westminster, and Worcester, by Iohn Racster minister of the word, and preacher.</title>
            <author>Racster, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850711</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850711</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15935</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10317)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15935)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1184:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true art of liuing well The right vse of things indifferent. The plaine foot-path to the paradise of God. Three sermons preached at Cambridge, Westminster, and Worcester, by Iohn Racster minister of the word, and preacher.</title>
                  <author>Racster, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 118 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Richard Field] for Thomas Clarke, and are to be sold at his shop in Paules church-yard at the signe of the Angell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15935:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15935:1"/>
            <p>THE TRVE ART OF LIVING WELL.</p>
            <p>THE RIGHT VSE OF things indifferent.</p>
            <p>THE PLAINE FOOT-PATH to the Paradiſe of God.</p>
            <p>Three Sermons preached at Cambridge, Weſtminſter, and Worceſter, by IOHN RACSTER Miniſter of the word, and Preacher.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Clarke,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Paules church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard at the ſigne of the Angell. 1605.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15935:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15935:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORIE, AND to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>outline of shield</figDesc>
                  <head>DEO ECCLESIAE TIBI.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hree words in one eſcouchion diſplaying three vertues in one man, towards God godlineſſe, to his countrey charitie, and goodneſſe to thee, <hi>Deo, patriae, tibi,</hi> to God, his countrey, and to thee, doth Maiſter <hi>Lambert</hi> dedicate his booke. Which inuention of his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſorting well with my deſire, though my deſert be farre ſhort of his, I will, God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>illing, in this act of dedicating this wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thleſſe worke of mine, try my skill how I
<pb facs="tcp:15935:3"/> can vſe his inſtrument, contenting my ſelfe, as welt I may, to be his ſecond. First, <hi>Deo, to God,</hi> as to my author, I the writer dedicate theſe my labours, my ſelfe, my whole life, and all my actions as God ſhall give grace. And this dedication brancheth it ſelfe out two wayes. <hi>Hallclu-iah,</hi> the dedication of praiſe, and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna,</hi> the dedication of prayer. It becometh vs well in all humilitie with thanks and praiſe to dedicate our workes to God, we being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto inſtructed by nature it ſelfe. All riuers pay tribute vnto the Ocean, thereby acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging their head, becauſe the ſea filleth them all, and ſupplieth all their wants: ſo muſt all ſoules give praiſe vnto God, acknowledging in him the fountaine of their eſſence or being, and the <hi>well</hi> of their being and doing well. <hi>Nam de plenitudine eius omnes bibimus, Of his fulneſſe we all haue drunke:</hi> all our wants are ſupplied from him, all our diſeaſes are cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in him, al our goodnes is procured through him, all our life is guided by him, all our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and ſaluation cometh of him, <hi>Omne datum, &amp;c. Fuery good giuing and eueric perfect gift is from aboue, &amp; cometh down from the father of lights. This alwayes with all thankfulneſſe we do acknowledge, moſt mightle, moſt mercifull, moſt glorious God
<pb facs="tcp:15935:3"/> and Father.</hi> And this is our <hi>Hallelu-iah,</hi> our dedication of praiſe vnto the Lord. Our <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna,</hi> our dedication of prayer, is <hi>Ana Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Salua obſecro; Ana Domine, da ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum obſecro:</hi> Proſper thy king O Lord, O Lord proſper thy kingdome here with vs: proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per euery word and worke tending to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing of thy kingdome, our king, thy Chriſt, our Lord and God. Proſper O Lord this word and worke of me thine vnworthy ſeruant, that being of it ſelfe but <hi>granum,</hi> a very ſmall thing in it ſelfe, but a graine, it may through thee be made <hi>ſemen,</hi> a ſeed, that is, of an eſfectual qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, where it is but of a contemptible quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And bleſſe the growth of this ſeed by being preſent with vs, as thou haſt bene with thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſeruants of old, that euery one of vs, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee to be the chiefe and true huſbandman, may pray and ſay vnto thee: Let my wordes O Lord drop as the raine, and my ſpeech diſtill as the deaw: as the ſhowre vpon the herbes, and as the great raine vpon the graſſe: ſo let thy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in my mouth make fruitfull the hearts of all that heare it. Thus doth praiſe and prayer commend this cauſe vnto the Lord. In the next place, next vnto God, is the Church of God; which being a vine will afford a ſhadow to ſuch as gather grapes; being an houſe miniſtreth a
<pb facs="tcp:15935:4"/> couering to the Miniſters that be vnder her roofe; and being the mother of vs all, doth cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably accept the meaneſt offerings and deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the meaneſt of vs all. Theſe be the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that aſſure me, that albeit, as in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall tabernacle, ſo likewiſe in the ſpirituall building of the ſpirituall temple, ſome bring gold, that is, workes of greater moment, others bring ſiluer, things of brighter and finer ſhew, others bring braſſe, matter of more ſtrength, and others there be that bring blew ſilke, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſcarlet, and fine linnen, that is, daintie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, delectable, curious, and coſtly: yet is it my hope ſtill, that my poore endcuors, my home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtuffe, whether haire or skins, or whatſoever elſe they ſhall be thought to be, will ſerue for ſome vſe or purpoſe in the Church: and my willing mind to do good (though attended but a little, and extended in effect but to a few) ſhall not be condemned, though it deſerue but ſlenderly to be commended. Firſt in all our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctios is <hi>God</hi> to be remebred, next the Church, thirdly ſome <hi>principall man in the Church,</hi> and laſtly the good of every common Chriſtian in this caſe is to be intended. The third point therefore is two fold: <hi>Tibi, to thee</hi> the <hi>patron</hi> of my paines, and <hi>Tibi to thee</hi> the reader of my bookes: the reading alſo being different, the
<pb facs="tcp:15935:4"/> one requiring an <hi>Emphaſis,</hi> and the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding an <hi>Antitheſis.</hi> Firſt <hi>Emphatic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>principaliter,</hi> emphatically and principally, putting a difference betweene the protector and the partner, betweene a father and a friend. <hi>Tibi to thee</hi> thou painfull pillar, and ſtout ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derd bearer of the Church: <hi>tibi to thee</hi> thou chiefi prelate of this our prouince: <hi>tibi to thee</hi> thou moſt famous Biſhop of a moſt fertile coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and faithſull people: <hi>tibi to thee,</hi> to thee, I ſay, thou reuerend father, the learned Biſhop of worthie Worceſter, to thee I commend and dedicate theſe whatſoeuer labours of mine, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring much in my mind, how to make known vnto the world, and your Lordſhip, how much, aſwel in the behalfe of my poore Church, whoſe caſe Itender as mine owne, as alſo in regard of my wretched ſelfe, formerly beyond all deſerts fauoured, I ſtand in all dutie bound to honour your Lordſhip: but I have bene too forgetful of my dutie herein. I do alſo confeſſe my weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vnworthineſſe herein: and even this is one of the degrees of happineſſe: <hi>primus foeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatis gradus eſt non delinquere, ſecundus delicta agnoſcere;</hi> it is the firſt and chiefeſt point of happineſſe not to offend, the ſecond is, to acknowledge our offences; ſaith <hi>S. Cyprian.</hi> Now therefore as a faithfull meſſenger of a
<pb facs="tcp:15935:5"/> gratefull mind, <hi>Tibi to thee</hi> I ſend this ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnt child of mine, it hath the maintenance of truth from the father of goodneſſe; O <hi>let it, let it</hi> haue the countenance of authoritie from your fatherly goodneſſe. This <hi>Tibi to thee</hi> is with difference and with preheminence: there is another without difference, and without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception: for he that publiſheth any thing can forbid none, but committeth his writings indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently vnto all without any exception at all. <hi>Tibi to thee</hi> that art learned, or art vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: <hi>Tibi to thee</hi> that art godly, or art vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Tibi to thee</hi> that art good, or art bad: to thee that art ſound of heart, or art not ſound: <hi>Tibi to thee,</hi> that loueſt learning, and Tiburn to thee that loueſt not learning: <hi>Tibi to thee,</hi> that hast money, and <hi>Tibi to thee,</hi> that hast it not: <hi>Tibi to thee</hi> that buyeſt, and <hi>Tibi to thee</hi> that borroweſt this booke: <hi>Tibi to thee,</hi> that paſſeſt by, and <hi>Tibi to thee,</hi> that comeſt in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to euery one ſeuerally ſparing none, but pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them ſecretly by the ſleeues: <hi>Tibi to thee</hi> belo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>geth to harken vnto the doctrine of truth. <hi>Tibi to thee</hi> that printeſt, that they may be ſold: to thee that ſelleſt, that they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y be bought; to thee that buyeſt, that thou maist read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; to thee that readeſt, that thou maiſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand; to thee that vnderſtandeſt, that thou
<pb facs="tcp:15935:5"/> maiſt beleeue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to thee that beleeueſt, that thou maiſt practiſe; to thee that practiſeſt, that thou maiſt continue: to thee that printeſt, ſelleſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> buyest, readeſt, vnderſtandest, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eleeueſt, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſeſt, continueſt, and perſeuerest in the word of truth, is this worke of truth committed. And thus we commit all to God, our ſelues with all. God ſaue England, and the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and people thereof: God bleſſe Worceſter, and the Biſhop thereof: God ſend vs all his grace. Suckley in Worceſterſhire: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Nouemb.</hi> the 6. <hi>Anno Dom. 1604.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all dutie and true loue, Iohn Racster.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15935:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15935:6"/>
            <head>THE TRVE ART of liuing well.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>MATTH. CHAP. 10. VER. 16.</bibl>
               <q>Be ye therefore wiſe as ſerpents, and innocent as doues.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cond Epiſtle to Timothie, the third Chapter and firſt verſe, the Apoſtle propheci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of our times: <hi>This know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that in the laſt dayes ſhall come perillous times.</hi> There is none that doubteth, but that theſe, wherein we liue, be the laſt dayes, and therefore it is more then certaine that theſe be the perillous times: wherein (as ſaith <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen</hi>) eſpecially to men of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, there be whole labyrinths of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15935:7"/> cares, whole faires of affaires, whole ſeas of troubles, whole worlds of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe which daily oppreſſe vs. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. All goodnes eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing hideth it ſelfe; all naughtineſſe bare-faced bluſheth not. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, our ſhip, that is our ſoule ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the night. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Chriſt is aſleepe, if not in the ſhip, yet in the ſoules and conſciences of men.</p>
            <p>In the 29. of Geneſis <hi>Rahel,</hi> that is <hi>ouis</hi> a ſheepe, beareth <hi>Beniamin,</hi> that is <hi>lupum rapacem,</hi> a rauenous wolf, in the 49. of Geneſis: but it coſt her her life for her labour; the ſheepe died in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell with the wolfe: <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 35. But in the beginning of this verſe, the words immediatly going before my text there is a greater danger: not <hi>partus,</hi> but, <hi>pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na luporum,</hi> not the birth of one, but the battaile of manie wolues of your ſoules. <hi>Ecce ego mitto vos, Behold I ſend you, tanquam oues, as ſheepe in the middeſt of wolues:</hi> which could not be without daunger of death. And therefore as a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15935:7"/> wiſe captaine, in theſe words he war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth and armeth vs and them againſt the dangerous conflict in this perilous time. <hi>Eſtote igitur: Be ye therfore wiſe as ſerpents, but innocent as doues:</hi> where there is not a word that hath not <hi>ſuum pondus</hi> his weight: nay euery word is <hi>pondus,</hi> it is a weight; for without this euery man hath his <hi>Tekel,</hi> that is, euery one is weyed in the ballance, &amp; found too light. <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. 27. But if wiſedome be in the one ſcale, that is, in our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and innocencie or ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie in the other, that is our will, we ſhall weigh ſomewhat in the ballance, that is in the eſtimation of Chriſt our Sauiour. The one is the weight of iudgement: <hi>Be ye wiſe as ſerpents:</hi> and the other the weight of iuſtice: <hi>and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent as doues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as we ſee in a caſe of weights, all of them be contained one in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo likewiſe the parts of this text ſtand like weights one within another. For firſt here be two precepts or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15935:8"/> 
               <hi>Be ye wiſe as ſerpents:</hi> this is the firſt precept; <hi>And innocent as doues:</hi> this is the ſecond. And theſe two precepts haue two vertues in them: the firſt is wiſedome, <hi>prudentes, wiſe as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents.</hi> The ſecond innocencie, <hi>innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, innocent as doues.</hi> And theſe two vertues haue two examples: <hi>Sicut ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentes, as ſerpents;</hi> this is the firſt exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or patterne: <hi>Sicut columbae, as doues,</hi> this is the ſecond patterne or example. Two precepts, two vertues, two exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, all of them one within the other waight-wiſe. For firſt, for the former precept, there is <hi>Eſtote, Be ye;</hi> this is the precept, then <hi>prudentes, wiſe,</hi> here is the vertue: and then, <hi>ſicut ſerpentes, as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents,</hi> here is the example. Againe for the later precept, firſt we muſt repeate <hi>Eſtote, Be ye,</hi> and this maketh the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, then <hi>innocentes, innocent,</hi> that is the vertue: and then <hi>ſicut columbae, as doues,</hi> this is the example. <hi>Be ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſe as ſerpents, and innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as doues. Eſtote, Be ye.</hi> To euery commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15935:8"/> there be annexed two eſtates <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the commanding and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded eſtates: and theſe two eſtates require two conditions: the one is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, authoritie in the commander: and the other is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, abilitie in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and theſe two iointly toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make good euery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement: <hi>poteſtas,</hi> authoritie in the ſuperiour to command; and <hi>potentia,</hi> power in the inferiour to do that which is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: and theſe two be compriſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this one word <hi>Eſtote, Be ye.</hi> Firſt for <hi>poteſtas</hi> the authoritie of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it is Chriſt that ſaith <hi>Estote, Be ye,</hi> and he is their and our Lord. <hi>Ioh. 13. Ye call me Lord and maiſter, and ye ſay well, for ſo I am:</hi> and therefore he hath good authority to command. Nay he is <hi>ſilius</hi> the ſonne of God, and in this regard he ſaith, <hi>Mat. 28. Data eſt mihi omnis pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas: all power or authoritie is giuen me, both in heauen and earth.</hi> Secondly for <hi>potentia,</hi> the ability of the Apoſtles and all true Chriſtians to obey this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15935:9"/> 
               <hi>Eſtote prudentes, Be ye wiſe:</hi> that alſo is taken from their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: for the words of Chriſt are able to make men wiſe: nay they are able to make the ſonnes of men the ſonnes of God: <hi>Ioh. 1. 12. As many as receiued him to them he gaue power to be the ſonnes of God.</hi> And therfore all they that heare the word of God and beleeue it, haue power alſo in ſome ſort to do it. For Chriſts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement is not <hi>Dictum,</hi> a meere word, but it is <hi>Dictum factum,</hi> a word done, it gineth ability of doing to all thoſe that hearken vnto it: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his word and his deed goeth together. And therefore no doubt this verie word <hi>Eſtote, Be ye,</hi> was his act to make them wiſe. And he continueth the ſame in the 20. of Iohn: for to thoſe that in this place he ſaith <hi>Eſtote, Be ye wiſe:</hi> to thoſe in that place he ſaith, <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipite, Receiue the holy Ghoſt:</hi> and with him <hi>Tetigiſſe</hi> is <hi>Docuiſſe,</hi> if the holy Ghoſt do but touch the heart, it tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth it wiſedome, and all goodneſſe.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15935:9"/> Thus you ſee the equitie of this <hi>Eſtote,</hi> this commandement, for ſo I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther call it, then an exhortation, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in two things: in the authority of the commander, which is Chriſt the ſonne of God, and in the abilitie of the Apoſtles, who are enabled by Chriſt and the holy Ghoſt. And from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of this commandement we may learne to know the iniquitie of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that ſwerue from this, which conſiſteth likewiſe in two points: either in vſurpation, in coming to authoritie; or in tyrannie in vſing it: when he commandeth that ought to obey, or that is comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that can not be done. And from hence all that be in authoritie either in Church or commonwealth, or haue anie place or calling in either of them both, may learne to examine themſelues, both in the cauſe &amp; effect of their calling. Firſt whether they haue Chriſts comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, Chriſts call for their calling: whether he ſaid vnto them, <hi>Eſtote, Be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15935:10"/> ye:</hi> Be ye Biſhops, be ye Magiſtrates, be ye Miniſters, or elſe they crept vnto it by corruption. But if they be ſo blind that they cannot ſee this ſimply in it ſelfe, then let them looke vnto it in the effect, let them conſider how they fit their place and calling, how able they are to go through with the workes of God: for whoſoeuer is called of God, is enabled of God; for they that haue from him <hi>Eſtote,</hi> haue <hi>Accipite</hi> alſo: to whom he ſaith, <hi>Be ye,</hi> to the ſame he ſaith, <hi>Receiue ye:</hi> Be ye, that you may receiue: Receiue ye, that you may be able to be ſuch as he willeth you to be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſtote, Be ye:</hi> thus much of this word ſingle by it ſelfe: now as it is ioyned to the reſt of the words of my text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Estote, Be ye:</hi> not <hi>ſicut ſerpentes, as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents,</hi> for the ſerpent is not to be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated of vs in all things, not in the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſerpent, but in the wiſdome of the ſerpent: <hi>Eſtote prudentes, Be ye wiſe as ſerpents,</hi> not firſt <hi>ſicut ſerpentes, Be ye as ſerpents,</hi> &amp; then <hi>prudentes, wiſe:</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15935:10"/> for then the poiſon ſhould beare ſway, and the wiſdome would be corrupted: but firſt <hi>prudentes, be ye wiſe,</hi> and then <hi>ſicut ſerpentes, as ſerpents,</hi> and ſo the wiſedome preuaileth, and the poiſon which is our corrupt nature, is purged and ſanctified by that heauenly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſtote igitur prudentes: Be ye therfore wiſe.</hi> This is the vertue, not that which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> maketh the forme of all moral vertues, but which Chriſt maketh the ground of Diuine politiques. <hi>Estote prudentes, be ye wiſe.</hi> Some deuide all Diuinitie according to the threefold vſe thereof into theſe three kinds: the one is ſchoole diuinitie, and that is in ſpeciall requeſt amongſt the Papiſtes: the other is preaching diuinitie, &amp; that is wholly ſtudied by the Puritanes: the third is politicke diuinitie, and that is put in practiſe amongſt all, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the Popes pallace and colledge of Cardinals; where you ſhall haue ſome, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are good neither
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15935:11"/> for the ſchoole, nor for the pulpit, yet becauſe they can lay a plot for a liuing, and plot a peece of knauerie, of policie I ſhould ſay, as well as anie of <hi>Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel</hi> his ſcholers, haue gotten great place in the Church, &amp; are highly eſteemed of for their gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; which gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theirs is pure policie: but as for poore Diuinitie, they ſeeme either not to haue it, or care not for to vſe it. O ſay they, it is not good in policie, when their conſcience telleth them it is good in honeſty. Theſe be wiſe men but without learning or honeſtie. And I aſſure you, beloued, when I conſider the courſe of the world, what plots, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies, and circumuentions be in the world, then I thinke men be too wiſe: but when againe I behold the want of religion, and <hi>the feare of God which is the beginning of wiſedome,</hi> as the Scripture ſaith, when I ſee they want the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of wiſdome, then I begine to think that they are not wiſe at all: then ſay I to my ſelfe, Surely Policie hath ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15935:11"/> Diuinitie: this policie that is accounted the wiſedome of the world is the diuels policie, to ſteale from man the wiſedome of God. For this I dare auouch, that <hi>Machiuel</hi> his policie, is as good as <hi>Achitophels</hi> diuinitie: but Chriſts diuinitie is better policie. For this containeth the purity and quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of all, without anie droſſe or dregs at all. Diuinitie, diſputing, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, practiſing hath here the right vſe: and this maketh the good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, right profeſſor, and true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. Let vs therefore now heare and learne this:</p>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Eſtote igitur prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: Be ye therfore wiſe.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Now I beſeech you vnderſtand and conſider that this heauenly wiſedome, to which we are in this place inuited, is of diuers kinds, or rather hath diuers degrees. The firſt is prouidence, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we do <hi>proſpicere,</hi> looke before vs, &amp; whereunto we are ſtirred vp: <hi>Prou. 6. Vade ad formicam ô piger: Go to the piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire ô thou ſluggard, ſhe prepareth her
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15935:12"/> meate in ſommer, and gathereth her foode in harueſt.</hi> And in the 10. of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs, verſe 5. <hi>He that gathereth in ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is the ſonne of wiſedome: but he that ſleepeth in harueſt is the ſonne of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion.</hi> An example hereof we haue in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> in auoiding ſpirituall euil in the caſe of <hi>Potiphars</hi> wife, and in ſtoring &amp; hoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp temporal goods in the place of <hi>Pharaos</hi> officer: <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.</p>
               <p>The ſecond kinde or degree of this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> wiſedome is circumſpection, not only <hi>proſpicere,</hi> to looke before vs, but on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ſide of vs: the definition is <hi>cautela contrariorum vitiorum,</hi> a diligent heed of auoiding contrarie vices; and the worke is to order the affections. To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of contrarie vices, it behoueth vs to be circumſpect, leſt in ſhunning co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe we fal into prodigalitie, or in auoiding raſhneſſe we become too fearefull; and therefore it is wiſedome to be circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpect, that is, to looke round about vs, &amp; to order all our affections. And to this purpoſe the holy Ghoſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15935:12"/> ſpeaketh: <hi>Prou. 4. Omni cuſtodiâ cuſtodi cor tuum, Looke to thine heart,</hi> and the affections thereof, <hi>with all diligence;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to ſay <hi>Cuſtodi, keepe,</hi> he firſt ſaith, <hi>Omni cuſtodiâ,</hi> with all diligence keepe thine heart; leaſt thou ſhut the doores on this ſide of the heart againſt thine enemies, and open the gates vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them on the other. This kind of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome they haue not, who do ſo ſhun pouertie or other preſent euill, that they fall into eternall euill; not vnlike vnto ſtarting horſes, which ſtarting and ſhunning ſhadowes, plunge them ſelues into true danger, from whence they cannot get out. And this kind or degree of wiſedome, is commended vnto vs in the firſt of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> in the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of a wheele that did runne round about, and in the ſimilitude of the rings in the wheele, which were round in a round; but eſpecially in the eyes in the rings: <hi>and their rings were full of eyes:</hi> the minde of a circumſpect man is like eyes in a ring, and rings in a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15935:13"/> wheele, which be round, ſee round, and runne round.</p>
               <p>The third kind of this heauenly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is diſcretion: and the worke hereof is not only as the firſt kind <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicere,</hi> to looke before vs; nor as the ſecond, <hi>circumſpicere,</hi> to looke round about vs: but it is <hi>introſpicere,</hi> to looke into matters. And this worke of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>introſpicere,</hi> to looke into things, is of two ſorts: the one is generall, to looke into all things, <hi>&amp; diſcernere,</hi> and to diſcerne betweene vertue and vice, betweene bad and good: &amp; the other is more particular; to looke into the good, <hi>&amp; pretium rerum aeſtimare,</hi> to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of euerie thing as it is woorth. The firſt worke of diſcretion is to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne betweene good and bad: for there be certaine vices, that beare the face of vertues. Crueltic is couered with the name of iuſtice, remiſnes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led lenitie, couetouſneſſe is cloathed like thrift, pride like liberalitie; ſo that a man may be deceiued in them: but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15935:13"/> he that is ſo diſcreet as to diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene good and euill, ſhall neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre the danger of the curſe, <hi>Iſa, 5. Wo be vnto you that call euill good, and good euill; darkneſſe light, and light darkneſſe.</hi> And he that is thus wiſe ſhall ſee and acknowledge, in the abundance of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall commodities great want, in the ioy of earthly pleaſures much ſorrow, in the inioying of worldly glory much ignominie, in the glorie of fleſhly beautie great deformitie. And this is the firſt worke of diſcretion. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is the good being ſeparated from the bad, <hi>pretium rerum aeſtimare,</hi> to iudge of the good as euerie parcell is worth; and this alſo is an high point of wiſdome, to know the price of things, and requireth the whole knowledge of all diuinitie, for there is none can prize anie thing without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the thing; and there is no true knowledge but in diuinitie. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we may know truly how to prize all things, wee muſt haue the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15935:14"/> knowledge of all Diuinitie; and that is ſet down by <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> in two words or ſyllables: <hi>Nouerim te, nouerim me:</hi> Giue me grace, ô Lord, ſaith he, that I may know thee, that I may know me. <hi>Nouerim te,</hi> that I may know thee to be the creator of heauen and earth: <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerim me,</hi> that I may know my ſelfe the worke of thy hands, and may in diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion demeane my ſelfe towards thee as one of thy creatures: <hi>Nouerim te,</hi> that I may know thee to be the redcemer of mankinde: <hi>Nouerim me,</hi> that I may know my ſelfe to be a grieuous ſinner, &amp; therupon in diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make meanes to be redeemed by faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>Nouerim te, nouerim me,</hi> that is, <hi>nouerim te in me:</hi> that is, Giue me thy grace ô God, that I may know thee &amp; me, that I may know thee in me, that is, that we may know the gifts of God that be in vs; that wee prize not our ſelues at a lower rate then God hath ſet of vs. God hath giuen vs immortall ſoules, which be more worth then all
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15935:14"/> this tranſitorie world beſides, he hath promiſed vs eternal life which is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many worlds; nay he hath bought vs, and putchaſed all this for vs with his moſt precious bloud, euerie drop wherof is worth ten thouſand worlds. And therefore ſeeing hee hath paid ſo deare a price for vs, let vs in diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion learne to know our owne worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and neith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſell our ſelues for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as did <hi>Ahah, who ſold himſelfe to worke wickednes in the ſight of God:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let vs ſell our heritage, to wit, euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, for a thing of nothing, a temporarie commoditie, a momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie pleaſure, a meaſe of pottage, as did <hi>Eſau.</hi> But let vs with <hi>S. Paul, account all things as loſſe and doung in compariſon of the croſſe of Chriſt and the benefits therof.</hi> And ſo we ſhall rightly looke into and iudge of the price of things, if we thus diſcreetly looke into matters. For the mind of a diſcreot ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is like the beaſts that were about the throne, that had eyes <hi>ante</hi> and <hi>retro,</hi> before and behind,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15935:15"/> 
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 4. 6. nay like the bodies of thoſe beaſtes, that were full of eyes within, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 4. 8.</p>
               <p>The fourth and laſt degree or kinde <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> of this wiſedome is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeaketh, that that directeth all the reſt, which determineth, what, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where and how any matter is to be brought to paſſe: and it ſhall be called by me Direction, becauſe it directeth all the reſt. And this kinde beareth the name of the <hi>Genus,</hi> &amp; is deuided by <hi>Tully</hi> in the ſecond of his Rhetorickes as the whole, into theſe parts: <hi>Prudentiae tres ſunt partes,</hi> there be three parts of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: <hi>memoria, intelligentia, prouiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. Memoria eſt, per quam animus repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit illa quae fuerunt.</hi> Memorie is that by which the mind recalleth thoſe things that are paſt: <hi>Intelligentia, per quam ea proſpicit quae ſunt,</hi> Vnderſtanding or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight is that whereby the minde ſpieth thoſe things that now are. <hi>Prouidentia, per quam futuri aliquid videtur antequa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> factum eſt,</hi> Prouidence is that whereby
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15935:15"/> the minde deſcrieth a thing to come long before it be done; and all theſe ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> when they be in courſe and order, be the worke of direction. <hi>Praeſentia, ordina,</hi> order (ſaith he) things preſent; <hi>futura prouide,</hi> prouide for things to come: <hi>Praeterita recordare,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member things paſt. And what is this but the work of direction in euery one of theſe? Order, remember, prouide, things preſent, paſt, to come: me thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that I heare the voice of a maiſter of a familie, giuing direction to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie. S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſetteth out this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter moſt elegantly by three particles: <hi>vnde, vbi,</hi> and <hi>quo:</hi> whence, where, and whither: and all this is brought in with a <hi>Conſidera,</hi> conſider, which implieth diſcretion. <hi>Conſidera vnde venis,</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whence thou comeſt, <hi>&amp; erubeſce,</hi> and bluſh for ſhame: <hi>vbies,</hi> where thou art; <hi>&amp; ingemiſce,</hi> and ſigh for ſorrow: <hi>quo tendis,</hi> whither thou goeſt, <hi>&amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremiſce,</hi> and quake for feare. Quake for feare, when thou conſidereſt of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15935:16"/> of the graue, whither thou goeſt; ſigh for ſorow whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou heareſt the wickedneſſe of the world where in thou art: bluſh for ſhame when thou ſeeſt the baſeneſſe of the earth from whence thou art taken: the earth that bare thee, breedeth wormes to deuour thee; the world that keepeth thee, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth wolues to deſtroy thee: the graue that expecteth thee, hath darkneſſe to couer thee: of our ſelues we can ſing no other ſong then that that hath bene ſung alreadie, though toanother tune &amp; in another caſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Miſer, per miſeru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, à miſero, ad miſerum:</hi> Miſerable man, goeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the miſerable earth, by the miſerable world, to the miſerable graue: neither is there anie remedie to be found for all this, but in the houſe of wiſedome, neither haue we any wiſedome but by direction; neither is there anie better direction in the whole Scripture then in this place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Eſtote igitur prudentes ſicut ſerpentes:</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15935:16"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be ye therefore wiſe as ſerpents.</hi> For here you haue heard the commandement of wiſedome, <hi>Eſtote, Be ye;</hi> and the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue it ſelf, <hi>prudentes, wiſe,</hi> and now you ſhal heate the example and ſee the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne. <hi>Sicut ſerpentes, As ſerpents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not <hi>Eſtote ſerpentes,</hi> Be ye ſerpents, nor <hi>eſtote ſicut ſerpentes,</hi> be ye as ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in all things, nor, <hi>eſtote malitioſi,</hi> or <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenoſi ſicut ſerpentes,</hi> be ye malicious or venemous as ſerpents: no nor <hi>eſtote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuti,</hi> be ye ſubtle to deceiue as ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: but, <hi>eſtate prudentes ſicut ſerpentes, be ye wiſe as ſerpents:</hi> where in there be three circumſtances, <hi>quid, à quo, quomodo. Quid,</hi> what we muſt learne, and that is, <hi>bonum ſerpentis,</hi> that which is good in the ſerpent, to wit, his wiſdome, choſe the good, and leaue the euill. <hi>A quo,</hi> of whom we muſt learne, <hi>à ſerpente,</hi> of the ſerpent the betrayer of man; we muſt not be aſhamed to learne good of our enemies, nay learne good of the euill if they haue anie, nay of the diuel him ſelfe if it were poſſible. Thirdly,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15935:17"/> 
                  <hi>quomode,</hi> how we muſt learne this wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the ſerpent: <hi>ſicut,</hi> as: <hi>ſicut,</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as, this is the meanes how to do it, if we conforme our ſelues to the wiſedome of the ſerpent; and that is to be done in three points. This <hi>ſicut</hi> is of three ſorts. The firſt (according to <hi>S. Hierom</hi>) is, that the ſerpent, for the ſauegard of his head, doth expoſe his whole bodie to danger, winding in &amp; couering his head with his whole bodie beſide, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. So we likewiſe for our head Chriſt Ieſus ought to neglect our owne liues, and all that is ours, to vndergo any calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie either in bodie or goods, ſo that we may, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, holde faſt the head vnto the end by a liuely faith in Chriſt Ieſus, who is our head, which we muſt ſtriue to hold faſt by the hand of faith, what danger ſoeuer befal vs. If we be Chriſts ſheepe, let the worlds wolues, in Gods name, take our fleece, &amp; teare our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kas, ſo we haue this wit with the ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15935:17"/> to keepe our head, we ſhall not loſe by the bargaine.</p>
               <p>The ſecond wiſedome of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to be imitated of vs, is, that the ſerpent <hi>ſtoppeth her eare at the voice of the charmer, charme he neuer ſo wiſely,</hi> as it is in the Pſalme; the charmer ſeeketh for a certaine poyſon in the ſerpents head which is medicinable: &amp; the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent to preuent him, and not be begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by his inchantments, ſtoppeth one of his eares with the earth, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his taile: ſo wiſe &amp; holy men do ſtop one eare with the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of death, and the other with the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of their owne frailtie, weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diligently by what and how many waies they may periſh, leſt they ſhould giue eare vnto the ſuggeſtions of the diuell. For this is both a ſpurre and a bridle, a ſpurre to goodneſſe, and a bridle from wickedneſſe: <hi>Whatſoeuer thou tekeſt in hand, remember the end, and thou ſhalt neuer do amiſſe: Eccleſ.</hi> 7. the laſt verſe.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15935:18"/>
               <p>The third wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dome of the ſerpent <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is, that he ſtrippeth off his old skin: for when he is waxen old, and beginneth to feele his bodie to be a burden vnto him, by reaſon of the corruption that is in him; he glideth himſelfe through ſome ſtraight hole, in ſome rocke, and ſo leauing his skin behind him, is made whole, and becometh young againe. And ſo we, ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine, Sicut ſerpens exuuias deponit, it a nos veterem hominem exuamus: As the ſerpent ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth off his old skin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo let vs put off the old man,</hi> if we will be wiſe as the ſerpent. <hi>Deponite vos, put off</hi> ſaith S. Paul, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the conuerſation in times paſt, the old man: Epheſ.</hi> 4. 22. Wherein there be two ſpeciall points to be paralleled in a Chriſtian life. The one is, <hi>Foranimis anguſtia,</hi> the ſtraightneſſe of the hole: for if the hole be wide, the ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth in without any great adoe, and paſſeth through alſo to no purpoſe, for he carieth his skin with him, although heleaue the place or hole behind him:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15935:18"/> &amp; therfore he choſeth a ſtraight or nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row hole. The ſecond is, <hi>Loci ſtabilitas,</hi> for though the hole be narrow, yet if the place be not firme it is to leſſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For as if the hole be too wide, he carieth his skin with him: ſo if the place be not firme, he carieth the hole with him; both the place and his skin goeth with him, and ſo his burden is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and therefore he chooſeth a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row hole, there is <hi>anguſtia,</hi> and a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row hole in a rocke, there is <hi>ſtabilitas,</hi> firmeneſſe or ſtabilitie: and theſe two are to be imitated of vs. Firſt for <hi>angu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia viae,</hi> the ſtraitneſſe of the way: <hi>Luk. 13. 24. Striue to enter in at the ſtrait gate;</hi> ſtriue to enter, there is difficultie in the action; at the ſtraite gate, there is <hi>viae anguſtia,</hi> the hard paſſage, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why we ſhould ſtriue is ſet downe <hi>Matth. 7. 14. Becauſe the gate is ſtrait, the may narrow that leadeth to life, &amp; pauci inueniunt, and few there be that finde it.</hi> The gate is ſtrait, no paſſage for 2. men at once, the old ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; the new man can not enter in together; but the old man
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15935:19"/> muſt be caſt off, and then the newe man may get in at this ſtraite gate. The gate is ſtrait, yea and the way is narrow too, it is hard for a man that is heauie loaden, to get ouer a narrow bridge, but if he wil go ouer, he muſt lay down his burden, and ſo paſſe ouer himſelfe. And ſo we, muſt caſt off vs the burden of ſinne by repentance, if we meane to walke in this narrowe way: the gate ſtraite, the way narrow, <hi>&amp; pauci inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niunt,</hi> and few there be that find it: it is no common roade high-way, wherein the blind and the lame do walke, but <hi>pauci inueniunt, few there be that find it.</hi> He muſt haue his eyes in his head, that is the eyes of his vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened with true wiſdome; and his feet ſound, that is, a good conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that entreth in with few into this gate, and walke in this way: for this is <hi>porta ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> and <hi>via vitae,</hi> the gate of ſaluation, and the way of life.</p>
               <p>Secondly, beſides the ſtraitneſſe of the way, there is required in the life of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15935:19"/> a Chriſtian, <hi>ſtabilit as petrae,</hi> the firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a rocke, that his ground may be good: for many of the heathen wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in a ſtraite way, and kept a ſtrict courſe of liuing: <hi>Cryſippus</hi> verie conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, <hi>Fabritius</hi> very abſtinent, <hi>Ariſtides</hi> verie iuſt, <hi>Socrates</hi> verie patient, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their ground was not good, though their way was ſtraite, all their good actions were nothing elſe, but <hi>ſplendida peccata,</hi> ſinne in ſilken appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell. And therefore the true Chriſtian, that meaneth to leade a new life, muſt <hi>manere in ſtabili propoſito,</hi> hauing his whole ſoule by faith ſetled and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon Chriſt, who <hi>is the true ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall rocke, 1. Cor.</hi> 10. 4.</p>
               <p>And this is, <hi>ſicut ſerpentes,</hi> as ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: as ſerpents couer your head in the day of battel, that the ſerpent ſlay you not: as ſerpents, ſtop your eares in the time of danger, that the ſerpent intrap you not: as ſerpents, ſtrip off your old man, that the old ſerpent out-ſtrip you not. Be ye therfore wiſe as ſerpents, becauſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15935:20"/> the ſerpent is your enemie. And this ſhall ſuffice, of the firſt precept, the firſt vertue, and firſt example.</p>
               <p>The ſecond precept, becauſe it is not <hi>explicitè,</hi> expreſly ſet downe with an <hi>Estote, Beye,</hi> as the former: but <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitè,</hi> infolded in this coniunction <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>and,</hi> therefore you muſt conceiue, that it was likewiſe <hi>implicitè,</hi> infolded in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folding the former, and ſo leauing this, as painters do their pictures to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered on the other ſide of the table, I come to the vertue &amp; example, which be ſpecified in my text.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>And innocent as doues.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>But firſt a word or two of the cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of both theſe precepts implied in the firſt particle <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>and.</hi> There is great affinitie betweene doing good &amp; eſchuing euill, and therefore both our Sauiour Chriſt here, and S. <hi>Paule</hi> elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, ioyneth them together as vnſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable companions. S. <hi>Paule</hi> in the 16 to the Romaines, verſe 19. both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth this place, and maketh the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15935:20"/> ſelfe ſame connexion that is here. <hi>Volo vos ſapientes eſſe in bono: I will that ye be wiſe in that which is good,</hi> that is, <hi>be ye wiſe as ſerpents. Simplices verò in malo: But ſimple in that which is euill,</hi> that is, <hi>and innocent as doues.</hi> Paules <hi>volo,</hi> and Chriſts <hi>eſtote</hi> is the ſame, but that the one is ſet downe in the obiect, and the other in the ſubiect. <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> in his <hi>paſtor: cap.</hi> 25. alledging this verie place ſaith, <hi>Valdè in electorum cordibus debet aſtutiae, ſerpentis, columbae ſimplicitatem aſtruere, &amp; ſerpentis aſtutiam columbae ſimplicitas temperare;</hi> In the harts of the elect the ſubtiltie of the ſerpent ought to vphold the ſimplicitie of the doue; and the ſimplicitie of the doue to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the ſubtiltie of the ſerpent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſtote prudentes ſicut ſerpentes, ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligendas fraudes:</hi> Be ye wiſe as ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) to vnderſtand their deceit: <hi>ſimplices ſicut columbae, ad ignoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendas iniurias,</hi> and ſimple or innocent as doues to pardon their iniuries. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nzen,</hi> he will haue the medley of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15935:21"/> theſe vertues to make a mixture: and this AND to be the phyſitions <hi>Ana. Be ye wiſe as ſerpents, AND innocent,</hi> this <hi>And</hi> is <hi>Ana:</hi> that is, take as much inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie as wiſedome: <hi>ana,</hi> of both alike; and then the whole doſis, the whole receipt he maketh in this ſort <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Goodneſſe mingled with knowledge. Now it is plaine, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, knowledge or vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, is in the former vertue in wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and is contained in this: <hi>Be ye wiſe.</hi> And therefore it is certaine, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> goodneſſe is in this later, in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie; contained in this, <hi>Be ye inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</hi> And I will ſhew and proue vnto you, that this is a principal vertue, more principall then iuſtice it ſelfe: And firſt to begin with the furtheſt degree of ſimplicitie.</p>
               <p>Some there be, that becauſe they ſee <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the words <hi>vis</hi> and <hi>ius</hi> to haue neither more nor leſſe, but the ſelfe ſame let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: therefore they thinke the things alſo to be neither more nor leſſe, but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15935:21"/> iuſt the ſelfe ſame: if they might, they thinke they haue right to doe as they liſt, and to haue what they like. Theſe haue neither part nor portion in this vertue: but yet this I will ſay for them, they come nearer to it then the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites: for the ſinnes of violence be ſimple, that is, ſingle: but the ſinnes of deceipt be double, both the ſinne and the deceipt. This is the one kinde of naughtie goodneſſe, that are good to none but themſelues. This is the firſt and worſt kind of ſimplicitie, the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of ſinne, which is, <hi>ſimpliciter malum,</hi> ſimply euill.</p>
               <p>The ſecond kinde of ſimplicitie is, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men be by nature ſimple without vnderſtanding, ſuch as we call inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents: and theſe, though they haue no ſhare in this commandement, yet are they better then the former. A foole is better then a violent or vniuſt man; for this, though it be <hi>ſimplex malum,</hi> a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple euill, yet is it not <hi>malum ſimpliciter,</hi> an euill ſimply, becauſe I take it to be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15935:22"/> 
                  <hi>malum poenae,</hi> not <hi>culpae;</hi> a puniſhment that is laid vpon them, rather then any fault of their owne.</p>
               <p>The third degree of ſimplicitie and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> innocencie is in them that carrie this minde, <hi>Neminem laedere,</hi> as <hi>Tullie</hi> ſaith, to hurt no bodie. And here ſimplicitie or innocencie entreth into the degrees of goodneſſe; it is a ſtep to goodneſſe to haue this conſeience, and to beare this mind, that thou wilt hurt no body neither by thought, word nor deed.</p>
               <p>The fourth degree is <hi>propulſare iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam, </hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> as the Orator ſpeaketh, not onely not to do iniurie thy ſelfe, but to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der others alſo from doing iniurie as much as in thee lieth; to be ſo far from hurting thy brother, that thou haſt a care of him that he be not hurt by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And this is a further degree of goodneſſe then the former.</p>
               <p>The fifth and laſt is, <hi>vince malum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, Ouercome euill with goodneſſe, Rom.</hi> 12. 21. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Not onely not to doe iniurie, which is good; but defend from iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15935:22"/> which is better: nay, not only not to do iniurie, and to defend againſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie; but to do good, that is, to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall, and that to thine enemie, to do good againſt euill. To do euill for good, is <hi>merè diabolicum,</hi> meere diuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; for ſo did he, in ſlandering, and tranſgreſſing againſt God who created him good: to do euill for euill is <hi>merè belluinum,</hi> meere brutiſhneſſe, for ſo do they which hurt and goare one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: to do good for good is <hi>merè hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum,</hi> meere humane; for ſo do we, for this is common courteſie amongſt men: to do good for euill, is <hi>merè diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> meere diuine; for ſo did Chriſt when he prayed for his enemies. And this is the true patterne of perfect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie: which maketh <hi>Dauid</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale vnto the Lord for iudgement: <hi>The Lord be iudge betweene thee and me,</hi> when he had done good for euil. 1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 24. This was <hi>Dauids</hi> innocencie, and this was Chriſts innocencie, and this innocencie is goodneſſe, &amp; this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15935:23"/> is better then righteouſneſſe, for it goeth a degree beyond it: <hi>Rom. 5. 7. Doubtleſſe a man would ſcarce die for a righteous man, but for a good man it may be one durſt die:</hi> where <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, is he that doth no iniurie, but dealeth vprightly with all. But this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is the neareſt to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a good man is he that doth good to all, to his power. And this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, this good man is Chriſts <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen</hi> implieth, and as the word it ſelfe may ſeem to implie: for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whoſe ſimple is to compound, is a compou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d word, &amp; yet it ſignifieth a ſimple man; which implieth thus much, that this <hi>ſimplex,</hi> is not a ſimple ſimple man, but a ſimple man, and a good man, that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in all ſingleneſſe, integritie, and ſinceritie of life: and this is the weight of our Sauiour his words in this place, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>and innocent.</hi> Now follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the laſt point, the patterne or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the later vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Sicut columbae, as doues.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15935:23"/>
               <p>The holy Scripture attributeth vnto Doues, both argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of praiſe, which the godly lay hold on, and matter of diſpraiſe, which the vngodly follow. The arguments of praiſe be, that they flie moſt ſwifily, lacke gall and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, feed not on dead ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kaſſes, loue cleare waters; all which be proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably anſwered in the quality of Gods children. But one thing is worthie the reprehenſion in them, that they are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily deceiued: and in this one thing the vngodly be like vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Oſe 7. 11. Factus eſt Ephraim ſicut columba ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta: Ephraim is like a done deceiued.</hi> But all is nothing to this place, but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie of the done. <hi>Be ye innocent as doues.</hi> And that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in two points, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the doue is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie violent paſſions, and without anie great hurt. For the firſt, <hi>S. Hierome</hi> writing vpon the ſeuenth of <hi>Oſee,</hi> ſaith, that other birds when their yong ones be taken from them, do fight before, &amp; mourne after they be gone; but the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15935:24"/> doue when her yong ones be taken, <hi>non dolet, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requirit:</hi> and ſo muſt thou, if thou beeſt the child of God: though thy children, that is, whatſoeuer is deare vnto thee, be taken from thee, <hi>non dolere,</hi> not to be ſorie, for <hi>the ſaurum habebis in caelo, Thou ſhalt haue treaſure in heauen: non requirere,</hi> neither muſt ye make anie great adoe to get them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, for <hi>dabitur vobis, it ſhall be giuen vnto you, ful meaſure, preſſed downe, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken together, and running ouer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſecond, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they are without hurt. <hi>Theophilact</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this my text writeth, that Doues, though they leeſe their yong ones, yet they returne <hi>ad coſdem dominos,</hi> to the ſame maiſters that robbed them: <hi>ad eaſdem aedes,</hi> to the ſame houſes that betraied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: nay, <hi>ad eoſdem nidos,</hi> nay they hatch againe in the ſame neſts that their other yong ones were killed in, ſtil enriching thoſe that ſtill ſpoile them. And ſo ought we by our Lord and maiſters commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>to him that ſmiteth vs on the one
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15935:24"/> Cheeke, turne the other: and he that would take away thy cloake, giue him thy coate alſo.</hi> And this is the ſence of this place, <hi>Be ye innocent as doues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſumme of all that hath bene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, is expreſſed by the Orator in two words vnawares: <hi>Ars viuendi:</hi> it is the art of liuing well, which exceedeth all other arts in the better part. The principles of all other arts be true only, but the leuell of life, or the art of liuing is both true &amp; good. This is <hi>ars archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectonica,</hi> the miſtreſſe art of all others: all other arts be but inſtruments of this art of liuing. The grounds of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, the arguments of Logicke, the perſwaſions of Rhetorike, the delights of Muſicke, the numbers of Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, the meaſures of Geometrie, the motions of Aſtronomie, be but inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and inuentions of men, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the vnderſtanding. All manuarie arts ſerue eſpecially for the bodie, as the art of plowing &amp; tilling the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, for the vſe of the bellie: the art of ſpin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15935:25"/> and weauing, for the cloathing of the backe: but this art of liuing maketh vſe of all other arts as inſtruments, and it furniſheth both the bodie and the ſoule with good and profitable things. It gouerneth the mind with wiſdome, knowledge and diſcretion; and this is the firſt <hi>Eſtote, Be ye wiſe.</hi> It ruleth the bodie by temperance, abſtinencie, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietic &amp; chaſtity; and this is the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Eſtote, Be ye innocent.</hi> It perſecteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, by the feare of God, and loue of our neighbours; and this is both the firſt and ſecond, both wiſedome and innoconcie. This is Chriſtian ethicks, the verie art of liuing: ſo that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out this leſſon, liueth by chaunce and not by art, becauſe he hath not the art of liuing. For he that is not wiſe, is caried away with euerie companie, vpon euery occaſion, vnto all naughtineſſe. And he that careth not to be innocent, with the drunkards plaieth the good felow, with the ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers is a forward gentleman, with adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15935:25"/> is a companion, with theeues he is a ſharer. And that you may ſee eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently that he liueth by chaunce, the Scripture ſaith plainely of ſuch a one, <hi>that a wauering minded man is vnſtable</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>in all his wayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But he that is <hi>ſapiens</hi> and <hi>innocens,</hi> wiſe and innocent, is <hi>quadratus,</hi> fower ſquared. Take a fower ſquare ſtone, &amp; toſſe it, tumble it, and caſt it which way you will, and it falleth alwayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there is no alteration, but ſtil there will be fower corners aboue, fower beneath, and fower on each ſide: ſo take a godly man, that is wiſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and turne him from aduerſitie to proſperitie, and from proſperitie to aduerſitie againe, and he will be ſtill the ſame, ſtill <hi>quadratus,</hi> fower ſquare. Aboue, that is in proſperitie, he hath fower corners; thankfulneſſe to God, friendlineſſe to his neighbours, pitiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the poore, gentleneſſe to all men. Beneath, that is in aduerſitie, he hath fower likewiſe; patience without
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15935:26"/> grudging, meekeneſſe without repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, hope without enuying, faith without wauering; and theſe be they that make a man innocent. On both ſides, that is, in both eſtates, he hath foure: prouidence, circumſpection, diſcretion and direction; and theſe be they that make a man wiſe: and theſe be they that neuer can be moued, what ſtorme of triall ſoeuer ſhall ariſe.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Eſtote igitur, &amp;c. Be ye therfore wiſe as ſerpents, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent as doues.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:15935:26"/>
            <head>THE RIGHT vſe of things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1. Cor. 10. 23, 24.</bibl>
               <q>23 <hi>All things are lawfull for me, but all things are not expedient: all things are lawfull for me, but all things edifie not.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>24 <hi>Let no man ſeeke his owne, but eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man anothers wealth.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE generall doctrine of theſe three Chapters, the eight, ninth, and tenth Chapters, is for the moſt part a direction for vs, <hi>in rebus medijs &amp; externis,</hi> in matters indifferent and externall things. For although God, who is a ſpirit, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. will be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in ſpirit and in truth, yet it is verie
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15935:27"/> materiall and auailable to Chriſtianity and true religion, that the Church be rightly ordered, and reformed in theſe outward, temporall, and indifferent matters: partly in regard of our ſelues, that wee by theſe outward exerciſes may be drawne into the meditation of heauenly things: and partly in reſpect of God, who will haue nothing to be done fainedly or counterſeitly. And therefore they are greatly deceiued, who do ſo greatly boaſt of the integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſoule, that in externall and outward affaires they thinke all things to be lawfull vnto them, and thereby apply themſelues to the wils and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of all men. The particular doctrine is concerning the right vſe of meates, how farre they be lawfull, and when vnlawfull. But the eſpecial point of theſe three Chapters which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Corinthians eſpecially, was the reproofe of the abuſe of diuerſe ſtraying Chriſtians amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who although they had giuen their names
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15935:27"/> to Chriſt, yet did they keepe company with idolaters, they did eate &amp; drinke with them euen thoſe meates which were the remainders of beaſts ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to idols: whereby the weake con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of many of their brethren were grieuouſly offended.</p>
            <p>We will ſtand vpon that doctrine which ſhall be agreeable to our times, and moſt profitable for this auditorie, following the generall doctrine in my expoſition, touching all indifferent things, &amp; externall, which compriſeth vnder it the particular doctrine of meates, and the ſpeciall, as concerning things ſacrificed to idols: and this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition wil be moſt profitable for you to heare, &amp; moſt eaſie for me to ſpeake of. Now therefore (that I may come to my text) theſe two Verſes containe two rules; the firſt is, <hi>lex veritatis,</hi> the law rule of truth, in the 23. verſe: the ſecond <hi>lex charitatis,</hi> the true rule of charitie, in the 24. verſe. More plainely thus; firſt here is a directiue explicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:15935:28"/> or a direction, by way of explication, which ſetteth downe <hi>verum</hi> the truth, in the 23. verſe; then here is an exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue application, or an exhortation to applie rightly the directions vnto our ſelues in the courſe of our liues, &amp; ſquaring of our actions accordingly, which implieth <hi>verum bonum,</hi> both true, and good. In the direction there be two parts, the firſt a <hi>maxima,</hi> or ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rule, <hi>Omnia mihi licent, All things are lawfull to me:</hi> which although it be <hi>ſimplex,</hi> ſingle, and but one in deede and ſence, yet <hi>verbis duplex,</hi> it is twiſe iterated in this place, <hi>Omnia mihi lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſed non omnia conducunt, All things are lawfull to me, but all things proſite not:</hi> and againe, <hi>Omnia mihi licent, ſed non omnia adiſicant; All things are lawfull to me, but all things ediſie not.</hi> Secondly a caution or limitation of this generall rule, and that is two fold. For although all indifferent things ſimply in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues conſidered, without regard of circumſtances, be ſimply lawfull, yet if either in regard of our ſelues they be
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15935:28"/> not expedient, or profitable to vs; or in reſpect of our neighbors and brethren they tend not to the edification of our brethren, but rather to their hurt, then be they to vs vnlawfull: <hi>Omnia mihi li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen, ſed non co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducunt: But al things be not profitable vnto me:</hi> this is the firſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Omnia mihi licent, ſed non omnia adificant: But all things do not edifie:</hi> this is the ſecond. So thatin theſe indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t matters, which may be either done or not done, we muſt briefly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider theſe two points: Firſt, whether it be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for vs to do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or not: ſecondly, whether they tend to the edifying of our brethren or not: if both theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre, then are they to be done; if both or either repugne, then are they not to be done, but to be auoided.</p>
            <p>The rule of charitie by way of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, both in regard of the matter and maner is two fold. For the matter, it either reſpecteth our ſelues or our neighbours: for the maner, it is either affirmatiue or negatiue: it regardeth our ſelues negatiuely: <hi>Nemo querat
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15935:29"/> quod ſuum eſt: Let no man ſeek that which is his owne:</hi> it reſpecteth our neighbour affirmatiuely: <hi>Sed quiſque quaerat quod alterius eſt: But let euery man ſeeke that which is anothers.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Omnia, All things.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Firſt for remouing of all doubt, and clearing of my text in all points from all ambiguitie, this queſtion commeth euen now into my minde: how this may be, that all things ſhould be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſeeing that manie and almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable things be altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and vtterly forbidden. If this were the rule, and thus roughly to be vnderſtood, then were it lawfull to ſweare with the ſwearer, to drink with the drunkard, to ſteale with the theefe, and to be a partaker with the adulterer, and ſuch like. To this I anſwer, firſt that we muſt learne of this our author, to make account of vnlawfull things as of ſinne, <hi>priuatiuè,</hi> priuatiuely, and not <hi>poſitiuè,</hi> poſitiuely, calling ſinne <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a tranſgreſſion of the law, or as <hi>Anſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:15935:29"/> defineth originall ſinne, to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but <hi>carentia originalis iuſtitia,</hi> a want of originall iuſtice: ſo is all ſinne nothing elſe, nor all vnlawfull things anie thing elſe, but a want of iuſtice, a meere want, and therefore a meere no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: and ſo <hi>Iuſtine Martyr</hi> telleth vs, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for euil and vnlawful things, ſaith he, by an euill, &amp; vnreaſonable vſe, and not by nature, are made euill: and if they be nothing in nature, then are they worſe then nothing in grace. All vnlawfull things therefore, and all ſins, <hi>quatenus &amp; quamdiu,</hi> ſo far forth, and ſo long as they are ſuch, both in nature, law, and grace, they are nothing.</p>
               <p>Secondly I anſwer, that it is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon rule, well knowne in ſchooles, <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſales voces non eſſe vltra terminos cauſae de qua agitur extendendas,</hi> that is, no vniuerſall voices or words are to be ſtretched beyond the confines of their cauſes of which they are ſpoken: and ſo in this place, in that he ſaith, that all
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15935:30"/> things are lawfull vnto me, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is thus to be vnderſtood and not otherwiſe, all dayes, diets and meates, all indifferent things are lawfull to me. This is the ſtate of the things: now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the caſe of law.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Licent, are lawfull.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>There is a <hi>licet neceſsitatis,</hi> a <hi>licet</hi> of neceſſitie, and a <hi>licet libertatis,</hi> a <hi>licet</hi> of libertie. For things may be ſaid to be lawfull either <hi>abſolutae néceſsitatis,</hi> of abſolute neceſſitie, and theſe include but one part of the contradiction, as to honor thy father is lawfull, but not to honor thy father is vnlawfull: to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God is lawfull, but not to worſhip him is altogether vnlawfull. On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, not to ſteale lawfull, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſteale vnlawfull, &amp;c. Or elſe things are called lawfull <hi>permiſsiuae li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertatis,</hi> of libertie permitted, &amp; theſe include <hi>vtramque contradictionis par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> both the parts of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradiction, both the affirmatiue and negatiue part: as to obſerue, and not obſerue a day is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15935:30"/> both alike, to eate meate is lawful, and not to eate meate is not vnlawfull; to weare ſome kind of apparell is lawfull, and not to weare ſome kind of apparell is likewiſe lawfull, &amp;c. And this is the <hi>licet,</hi> which our Apoſtle ſpeaketh of here, the <hi>licet</hi> of libertie of permiſſion, or permitted libertie in matters indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent. This is the priuiledge of the new Teſtament aboue the old; libertie aboue law, and law aboue law; the law of libertie aboue the law of feare. The Law ſaith, to touch a dead carkas defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a man, and maketh him vncleane, <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. But libertie ſaith, <hi>Omnia mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nu, 19. 1</note> 
                  <hi>mundis:</hi> All things are cleane to the cleane: <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 15. The law of feare ſaith, as the miniſter of grace telleth vs, touch not, taſt not, handle not, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 21. But the law of libertie ſaith, <hi>Ariſe Peter, kill and eate, Act. 10. 13. The things that God hath purified pollute thou not, Act.</hi> 10. 15. The old Teſtament ſaith, many things are vnlawfull, in ſo much as to weare a garment of wollen and linnen,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15935:31"/> and to plow with an oxe and an aſſe is vnlawful, <hi>Deu.</hi> 22. 10. 11. and that many beaſts, manie foules, many fiſhes are<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 11.</note> vnlawfull to be eaten. But the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (as here you may ſee) telleth vs, that <hi>Omnia mihi lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> all things are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to me: I know and am perſwaded through the Lord Ieſus, that nothing is vncleane of it ſelfe: <hi>Rom. 14. 14. Non quaero quo veſcaris, ſed quo delecteris:</hi> I demand not what thou doeſt eate, but wherewith thou art delighted (ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine.</hi>) And <hi>S. Paule</hi> reporteth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that the Iewiſh ceremonies be<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 4. 9.</note> now <hi>impotent and beggerly rudiments:</hi> and that one word, which is, <hi>Domino,</hi> to the Lord, will ſerue for all; ſo all be done in the Lord, and to the Lord, all is well. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 6. He that obſerueth the day obſerueth it to the Lord: and he that obſerueth not the day, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it not to the Lord: He that eateth eateth to the Lord, for he giueth God thanks: and he that eateth not, eateth not to the Lord, &amp; giueth God thanks.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:15935:31"/>
               <p>And this <hi>In Domino,</hi> in the Lord, or to the Lord, as it requireth our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with ioy, &amp; our ioy with thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, &amp; all things in good order, and our order to be ſubalterne to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God: ſo doth it <hi>ipſo facto</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarietie, &amp; ſubcontrarietie to God, that our law caſe may alwayes haue a reference to our law-giuer. Wherefore we muſt take heed that we be not contrarie to the Lord, in doing any thing oppoſit to the expreſſe word of God, neither be ſubcontrarie vnto him in reſiſting the ſubſtitute of God, who hath a commiſſion from God, for the right ordering of theſe matters vnder God; for here goeth out the date of this licence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Omnia mihi licent, All things are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>This was a common ſaying among them, which they tooke vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as a ſpecial warrant of Chriſtian libertie, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the chiefe Iuſtice of peace Ieſus Chriſt, who hath made peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15935:32"/> heauen and earth, God &amp; man. And indeed it ſeemeth to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all externall indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t things, as to eate, to drinke, to weare this or that apparell is lawfull for me, yet is it not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, vniuerſally to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. True it is, <hi>Omnia licent,</hi> but yet not <hi>omnibus perſonis, omni tempore, &amp; omni loco:</hi> all things are lawfull, but not to all men, at all times, and in all places; neither yet, which is a principal matter <hi>omni modo,</hi> in euerie forme or manner. As for example, to eate fleſh is lawfull, but not in time forbidden by the law of our country: for <hi>ſi adres medias prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pet. 2. 13</note> 
                  <hi>accedat, fiunt neceſſariae:</hi> to buy &amp; ſell is lawful, but not in the Church:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>t 21. 12 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ut 6. 13 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>od 20. 7</note> to ſweare is lawfull, but onely before a Iudge, to end ſome controuerſie: to ſleepe is lawfull and natural, but not in<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 20. 9.</note> the Sermon time: to weare apparel not forbidden; but for a Miniſter to go like a ruffian, or not to vſe decent habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liments in the Church, is a thing offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue and not ſo lawfull; neither is the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15935:32"/> manner alwayes allowable, as <hi>animo contradicendi,</hi> with a gainſaying minde and purpoſe, to feaſt on good Friday, and faſt at Chriſtmas, which thing is reproued by <hi>Caluin</hi> himſelfe. Not that<note place="margin">Inſtit. lib. c. 19. ſect</note> either he or we, put or place any reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the things themſelues, either in obſeruing of a day or not, in eating or abſtaining from fleſh, in wearing or not wearing of this or that kind of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, or ſuch like: but becauſe, as one ſaith: <hi>Sunt in homine veluti mundi duo, quibus &amp; varij reges, &amp; variae leges prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe poſſunt:</hi> Two worlds as it were, be in a man, one reſembled in the ſoule, the other in the bodie, two kings ouer theſe two worlds, Chriſt, and Chriſt his deputie the lawfull magiſtrate; two kinds of lawes correſpondent to all the reſt, Ciuil or poſitiue law of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey from the king thereof; ſpirituall &amp; eternall of the Church, from Chriſt her head. The ſpirituall kingdome of Chriſt yeelding vnto the politique or ciuill kingdome of the Lieutenant of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15935:33"/> Chriſt, ſome authoritie here on earth, for ordering &amp; gouerning the Church in theſe indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and external things, and omitting ſome matters, willingly as of purpoſe to be ordered by him; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>in elementis,</hi> in the elements or ſimples of our profeſſion, and in the infancie of the Church, being at that time a meere Church ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bodie politique, <hi>Beda</hi> his rule is both true and certaine, <hi>licita tractanda erant non praeſcripto legis, ſed conſilio charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> Lawful things were to be vrged not by the ſtrictneſſe of the law, but by the counſell of charitie, yet <hi>in mixtis &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitis,</hi> in the mixt and compound, the ſtates being incorporated, &amp; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements compounded in the floriſhing and eſtabliſhed ſtate of the Church, the Kings commaundement being backed and ſeconded by God himſelfe, and his Church being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto him, there is euen in theſe indifferent things ſome conſcience to be made, and ſome religious order to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15935:33"/> be obſerued. Neither thinke I that any man ought ſo ſtifly to ſtand or ſticke v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Chriſtian libertie herein, whereas there being but three parts of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> libertie, the laſt and leaſt of all the reſt conſiſteth and is in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in things indifferent: &amp; a plain rule of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle is broken, and a manifeſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God contemned, in reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting<note place="margin">Rom. 1 Exod. 2</note> authoritie euen in theſe indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t matters. This therefore was the error of the Corinthians, which the Apoſtle propoundeth in his owne perſon, and taxeth them for by a conceſſion, that they thought that this was Chriſtian libertie, that they might at all times, in all places or occaſions, vſe or not vſe theſe indifferent things. And this is a point of diſcretion in the Apoſtle, that he doth not by an inuectiue ſharply reproue them, but ſpeaking in his own perſon, he moſt wiſely teacheth what they ſhould do in theſe caſes. But in that he doubleth it, <hi>Omnia mihi licent, All things are lawfull to me:</hi> and againe,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15935:34"/> 
                  <hi>Omnia mihi licent, All things are lawful;</hi> the reaſons may be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did oftentimes rehearſe this ſaying, that all things were lawfull to them: or elſe becauſe of the double dammage which happened vnto them hereby. Firſt in that they prouoked the Lord Gods diſpleaſure againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, in that they were partakers of the table of diuels. Secondly, in that they hurt and deſtoryed the weake co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of their brethren, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened the hand of the wicked in their idolatrie, by this their indiſcreet action and fact, and ſo offended againſt our Apoſtles diuinity principle in another place, <hi>Let al things be done to edification:</hi> and this is our Apoſtles meaning and ſence in this place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Omnia mihi licent, All things are lawfull for me.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>In the fourteenth chapter to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines the twentieth verſe, this part of my text ioyned to the part following, hath a commentarie; <hi>All things indeed
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15935:34"/> are pure</hi> ſaith he there: that expreſſeth what he meaneth by <hi>all lawfull things</hi> here. <hi>All things are lawfull,</hi> that is, there is not now vnder Chriſt as there were vnder <hi>Moſes,</hi> many things impure; but all things are now indeed pure empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically: <hi>But,</hi> ſaith he here, <hi>but</hi> ſaith he there; but yet ſay we, therefore this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not thus to be left thus vnlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; there is a further matter to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. Wherefore it followeth here: <hi>But all things are not expedient.</hi> Which the commentarie in that place expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in more plaine words: <hi>but it is euill for the man which eateth with offence:</hi> ſo that a man may vſe things, or rather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe things lawfull in them ſelues to the hurt of himſelfe, that is, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> things indifferent are done with offence: for this hath a <hi>vae,</hi> a wo denounced againſt it by Chriſt himſelfe: <hi>vae homini per que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſcandala: wo be to that man by whom of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences come.</hi> Wherefore for a further commentary of this commentary, you ſhall take the old diſtinction as it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15935:35"/> vſed: there is <hi>ſcandalum accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> an offence taken: &amp; there is <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalum datum,</hi> an offence giuen. But as for <hi>ſcandalum acceptum,</hi> an offence ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken where none is giuen, neither is there anie <hi>vae,</hi> anie wo denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it by Chriſt, neither is it the euill ſpoken of by <hi>S. Paule:</hi> for euen our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour himſelfe (who was without ſin, and therefore without euill) had not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this ſcandal, this offence taken at his wordes, which were the words of truth, and at himſelfe who is truth it ſelfe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. It is therfore <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalum datum,</hi> a ſcandale or an offence giuen, which cauſeth the woe to him that bringeth it, and bringeth the euill to him that cauſeth it. To ſhew and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate this point in the matters that we haue in hand, as alſo to be a further commentary to both the former com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, take the ſixth Chapter of this Epiſtle, verſe 12. the tenure where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be theſe: <hi>Omnia mihi licent, ſed non omnia conducunt, &amp;c. All things are
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15935:35"/> lawfull for me, but all things are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient: all things are lawfull, but I am not brought into ſubiection of any thing:</hi> which place teacheth vs, firſt, that which this place alſo doth, that our <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> muſt haue a <hi>conducunt,</hi> our law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful muſt be profitable to our ſelues and others, or elſe our libertie without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, will be nothing but the abſtract of <hi>licet, licentia,</hi> a meere licentiouſnes: ſecondly, that in this our libertie, we are put in mind of our ſeruice to God, in that he ſaith in that place, that he is brought into the ſubiectió of nothing. For this is the libertie of the ſeruants of God, that they muſt ſerue him onely, and not be ſubiect to anie other thing, neither to principalities nor powers, to Angels nor Archangels, much leſſe to the elements, the baſer things of this world. This diſableth the authoritie of the things ouer man, &amp; enfranchiſeth or ſetteth man at liberty fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the things; but it doth not diſable the authority of man ouer the things, or diſchargeth
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15935:36"/> man from the authoritie of man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding a decent order to be kept in the right vſe of the things.</p>
               <p>Now then ſeeing that theſe lawfull things whereof the Apoſtle maketh mention in this place, be partly the bounds of Chriſtian libertie, and this libertie is but the libertie of ſeruants: therfore as we ſee here among vs, thoſe ſeruants deſerue eſpeciall commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that be firſt profitable themſelues, and then ſtirre vp others to become good ſeruants: ſo they do eſpecially vſe their Chriſtian libertie well, who firſt regard <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whether the thing lawfull be profitable, and then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whether it edifieth or not. For he onely is the good and faithfull ſeruant of God, who in all things ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to aduance the kingdom of God: and therefore our Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place ſaith of himſelf: <hi>Omnia om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus factus ſum: I am made all things to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. 9. 22</note> 
                  <hi>all men:</hi> there is the practiſe of this <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia licent,</hi> all things are lawfull. If you
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15935:36"/> aske him to what end: he will anſwer, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>That I may winne, that I may ſaue,</hi> both in one verſe; both words of profite, which is the firſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation: the firſt exerciſe of <hi>conducere</hi> to profite, is <hi>lucrefacere</hi> to gaine: the next is <hi>ſaluos facere,</hi> to ſaue or keepe ſafe. If further you demaund, what he would winne or ſaue, his anſwer is <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nullos; vt lucrefaciam infirmos, vt ſaluos faciam nonnullos, that I might win the weake, that I might by all meanes ſaue ſome:</hi> there is the ſecond point of this place, to wit, edification.</p>
               <p>What greater helpe vnder God to all this in theſe indifferent things then conformitie, where brethren go hand in hand, and all draw one way, and all follow one courſe? What greater hurt then confuſion, where the minds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſtracted, the workmen are diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and the worke is diſſolued? Let this therefore be the triall who giueth the ſcandale or offence, he that confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth himſelfe, that iointly with his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15935:37"/> brethren and fellow labourers he may ſet forward the worke; or he that ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth and ſecludeth himſelfe, for ſmall matters, left at libertie to be done or not to be done (ſauing only that herein we are tyed to the ordinance of man, as the authoritie appointed by God) thereby breeding confuſion and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the Church, thereby making a breach amongſt brethren, thereby lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſtumbling blocke in the way of the weake, thereby laying open a gap to the enemie, and thereby bringing hinderance to the worke of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Thus much of the <hi>maxima</hi> and the two limitations thereof iointly, now ſeuerally a word or two of either of theſe two limitations. The firſt limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that reſtraineth libertie that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth not licentious, is <hi>conducunt,</hi> if they haue an eye that they vſe not their libertie in anie thing that ſhal not be expedient or profitable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bonum autem expediens,</hi> is of diuers ſorts; for either it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15935:37"/> profit, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, in keeping that which is gotten, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifieth &amp; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs that which is expedient: for as in the ſtate of our bodie we ſay, that in one reſpect <hi>medicina</hi> is <hi>ſana,</hi> phyſicke is healthfull, becauſe it cauſeth &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth health; in another reſpect we ſay, that <hi>cibus</hi> is <hi>ſanus,</hi> our diet is healthfull, and <hi>exercitation ſana,</hi> our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe is healthfull in that it preſerueth our health, in another <hi>vrina eſt ſana,</hi> the water is a ſound or healthful water, in that it ſheweth the partie whoſe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine it is to be both healthful &amp; ſound: ſo likewiſe in our ſoules, the ſpirit and word of God is the health of our ſouls, in that by theſe bleſſings our ſoules health is procured and preſerued to vs. But our words and works they be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they alſo may be ſaid to be ſound and healthfull, as far forth as they be ſignes of the ſoundneſſe of the heart, and frutes of the ſpirit wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by loue. And in the whole church
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15935:38"/> and gouernment thereof, as confuſion and diſorder be ſignes of diſtempered humours, ſo conformi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and good order be, in theſe indifferent externall things, manifeſt ſignes of the eucraſie and good heal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h of the Church. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther onely are theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſignes in vs of the grace of God, but they may be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in others by the good ſpirit of God woorking together in their harts: <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they ſeeing your good works may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie your father which is in heauen.</hi> Thus is your <hi>licet</hi> to be limited with <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducit,</hi> your lawfull to be accompanied with profitable. I might ſet out this point by another ſimilitude of the getting, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and ſhewing foorth of riches: As firſt the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the efficient cauſe of riches is the gift of God: <hi>The bleſsing of God maketh rich;</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the keeping of them is in the wiſedome of man by the bleſſing of God: but the ſigne of riches, be liberall actions and workes which ſhew and ſet foorth the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15935:38"/> riches of anie man, both inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and outwardly, more then anie bragges or boaſtes of riches whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: and the holy Ghoſt ſeemeth in the Scripture to haue an ayme at this ſimilitude, where he ſaith, <hi>Be rich in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 61</note> 
                  <hi>good works,</hi> that is, as <hi>S. Iames</hi> aduiſeth vs to <hi>ſhew</hi> or ſet forth <hi>faith by works,</hi> that<note place="margin">Iames 2. 1</note> they may be both expedient to your ſelf in the growth and increaſe of faith, and profitable to others to ſtirre them vp to newneſſe of life, and edification, which is the ſecond point towardes which I haſte; onely thus much by the way, <hi>Caiphas</hi> tooke a wrong courſe, that applied <hi>lic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t</hi> to <hi>expedit,</hi> it is lawfull becauſe expedient, when rather he ſhould haue limited <hi>licet</hi> by <hi>expedit,</hi> firſt haue conſidered whether it were lawful that one man ſhould die for the ſinnes of the people, and then haue brought in his plea of <hi>expedit,</hi> it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient that one man ſhould die that the whole nation periſh not. The like impious ſentence was that of the Pope
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15935:39"/> of Rome, when he adiudged the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plars to ſodaine deſtruction: <hi>Etſi non licet per viam iuſtitiae, licet aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per viam expedientiae.</hi> Although (ſaith he) it be not lawfull by the way of iuſtice to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, yet notwithſtanding it is lawfull by the way of expediencie; a moſt ſenſleſſe ſentence, and altogether not beſeeming his holineſſe, as though any thing could be expedient, that is not iuſt and lawfull: many things are iuſt and lawfull which are not expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, not any otherwiſe. But I come to the ſecond limitation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Sed non omnia aedificant: But al things edifie not.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>This is the ſecond limitation, and it raiſeth the ſtate of Chriſtianitie a ſtep higher, for <hi>licet,</hi> without <hi>expedit,</hi> lawful and not profitable, is good law, but naughtie policie, <hi>expedit,</hi> without <hi>aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat,</hi> profitable &amp; not edifying is good policie, but naughtie diuinitie: <hi>licet, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedit, aedificat,</hi> lawfull, profitable, and edifying, is good law, policie and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15935:39"/> So that the true Chriſtian, muſt neither let his cauſe hang in <hi>licet,</hi> the common pleas, where is all law, and not ſo great reſpect of conſcience, nor in <hi>expedit,</hi> the Kings bench, where is both law and profite, but ſmall regard of religion; but he muſt bring it to <hi>aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat,</hi> the court of conſcience or Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie, where both law and profite be tempered by charitie.</p>
               <p>I might alſo compare theſe three words to the three parts of the Bible, the Law, the Prophets, &amp; the Goſpell, <hi>licet eſt legis vocabulum,</hi> lawfull, is a law terme, <hi>expedit eſt Prophetarum vox,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, is the Prophets voice, but <hi>aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat,</hi> but edifying is the Goſpels ſpeech: but this may ſuffice of this point: only I wil adde this, that <hi>aedificat,</hi> edification is both <hi>finis legis veritatis,</hi> the ende of the law of truth, in this verſe; and alſo <hi>principium regulae charitatis,</hi> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the rule of charitie, in the next: that as words of truth muſt tend to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification, ſo all workes of charitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15935:40"/> from edification; and therfore vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this principle of truth, is grounded and followeth this precept of charitie: <hi>Let no man ſeeke that which is his owne, but euery man anothers wealth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Nemo quaerat quod ſuum eſt, &amp;c. Let no man ſeeke that which is his own.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>This 24. verſe I ſaid was <hi>regula cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis,</hi> the rule of charitie, and that I will now proue by conferring the two parts of this verſe with two other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture. The firſt is in the 13. Chapter of this firſt Epiſtle to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: <hi>Charitie ſeeketh not thoſe things that be her owne:</hi> what elſe ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle here: <hi>Let no man ſeeke that which is his owne;</hi> but onely he applieth that here by particular exhortation, which before he deliuered in vniuerſall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. The ſecond place is in the firſt to the Corinthians. 8. 1. <hi>Charitas aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, Charitie edifieth.</hi> What elſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth he in this place by the affirmatiue p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t, when he willeth vs that euery man ſhould <hi>ſeeke that which is anothers,</hi> but
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15935:40"/> that we ſhould endeuour to edifie one another?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Nemo quaerat quod ſuum eſt. Let no man, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>This leſſon is too much and yet not enough learned of worldly men; too much in one ſence, in that there be ſome kind of men, that becauſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle forbiddeth euerie man that he ſhould ſeeke his owne; and no man can call any thing <hi>ſuum,</hi> properly his own, but ſinne, tranſg eſſion, corruption, &amp; ſhame; <hi>ſua peccata, ſua fraus, ſuum ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, ſua iniquitas:</hi> their ſinnes be their owne, thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deceipts, their wickednes, and their iniquities; therfore they will hudwinke them ſelues wilfully that they may not ſee and ſeeke to find out their owne ſinne and wickednes, that they may heale them: theſe miſtaking the marke do ouer-ſhoote it on the left hand. But if you do <hi>dextrè intelligere,</hi> rightly vnderſtand it, the whole world cometh ſhort of it. <hi>Let no man</hi> (to wit,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15935:41"/> in the vſe of Chriſtian liberty) <hi>ſeeke his owne,</hi> that is, <hi>quod ipſi licet libet:</hi> for as it was the ſpeech of an inceſtuous mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>ſi libet, licet,</hi> to make luſt a law: ſo <hi>quicqu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>id licet, libet,</hi> to do whatſoeuer we may do by law, is the part of a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine Chriſtian. We muſt ſomtimes <hi>decedere de iure noſtro,</hi> depart from our owne right, euen as Chriſt Ieſus being the ſonne of God did humble himſelf,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il 2. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>ſub forma ſerui,</hi> vnto the ſtate of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, for our ſakes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Sed quiſque quaerat quod alterius est. But let euery man ſeeke anothers wealth.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>This part alſo is too much followed of ſome in the wrong ſence, and too li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of all in the true: for to ſeeke other mens commodities to drawe them to themſelues, to ſeeke other mens goods for their own vſe, is ſo common a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, that it ſeemeth that men haue no need to be inſtructed in this point: but to ſeeke other mens wealth ſo that they will do nothing that may giue iuſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15935:41"/> to the leaſt, &amp; will do any thing that may edifie the moſt men, herein they are ſuch dunces &amp; non proficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that men will not learne, no though they be inſtructed by the ſpirite of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Quod alterius eſt, That which is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>This word <hi>alterius,</hi> anothers, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the action of ſeeking to be a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue action, and this relation of all our actions and endeauors in things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent vnto the good of others, is to be conſidered either in common, or in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall. In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, euery man is bound to maintaine with all might &amp; maine, nay to preferre, the common good of Church or commonwealth before his owne priuate gaine or commoditie. The heathen Oratouis inſtruction is worthie the attention of Chriſtians in this point: As we are not borne of our ſelues, ſo we are not bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne to or for our ſelues alone: one part of our life our wiues and children will take vp, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15935:42"/> part our friends and kinsfolke, and the greateſt part of all our country and commonwealth doth challenge of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to belong vnto it. And as this is the part of euerie man, ſo more chiefly of thoſe whoſe perſons are fitted to this purpoſe; publique perſons muſt ſeeke the publique commoditie before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the common good before their owne and proper welfare. The publike perſons office and good is in ſome ſort deſcribed by the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher: <hi>Omnium ſomnos illius vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantia defendit, omnium otium illius la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, omnium delicias illius induſtria, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium vacationem illius occupatio:</hi> His of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and care preſerueth the eſtate of al, and procureth the good of all; all mens ſle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe his watchfulneſſe, all mens eaſe his labour, all mens delights his indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, all mens vacation his occupation. Theſe publike perſons be of two ſorts: the Magiſtrate, and the Miniſter. An example of a good magiſtrate we haue in <hi>Moſes,</hi> whoſe zeale for the common
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15935:42"/> good of Iſraell was ſo great, that for their ſakes he deſired to be razed out of Gods booke. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 33. An example of a good Miniſter we haue in <hi>Paule,</hi> who for the benefite of his brethren could wiſh to be ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 3. Thus is this relation, or rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue action of ſeeking anothers good to be conſidered in common: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in ſeueral it hath three combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or relatiue coniugations. One an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, may be either the ſuperiour to his inferiour, the equall to his equall, or the inferior to his ſuperior, and euerie one of theſe haue ſeuerall duties which be his owne, and pertaining vnto him, and ought of dutie to be performed vnto him of the other: the inferior to his ſuperior muſt giue <hi>reuerentiam</hi> and <hi>obedientiam,</hi> the equall to his equall ſupplie, <hi>auxilium</hi> and <hi>conſilium,</hi> the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to his inferior muſt repay <hi>cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam</hi> and <hi>diſciplinam.</hi> A word or two of either of theſe, and ſo an end. The duties that the inferiour oweth to his
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15935:43"/> ſuperiour, be reuerence &amp; obedience; reuerence, as the homage of his bodie in all outward behauiour, as well in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as to riſe vp to him, &amp; vſe ſome action of ſubmiſſion, as in word, not to ſpeake without due regard to whom he ſpeaketh, and that the countenance be voide of all proud and diſdainfull lookes; &amp; in a word, that all his ieſture and outward behauiour be ſo ordered, that the ſuperiour may haue no excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the cariage of his inferiour towards him. But yet this is not all, for obedience bindeth the inferiour more nearely to his ſuperiour, for it tieth his ſoule in ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Let euery ſoule</hi> (ſaith our Apoſtle) <hi>be ſubiect to the ſuperiour power.</hi> If thy bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to wit, the Magiſtrate, thy maiſter, thy father, or anie that is in authoritie ouer thee, commaund thee any thing, ſo thou doeſt it, thou thinkeſt thou haſt diſcharged thy dutie; but I tell thee whoſoeuer thou art, if thou doeſt it mutteringly or vnwillingly, thou
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15935:43"/> haddeſt as good not do it at all, for thou oweſt obedience, that is ſoule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruice, vnto thy ſuperiour, but thou canſt not ſerue in ſoule but by the will, and therefore he that is vnwilling doth not obey.</p>
               <p>What account the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinke you make they of the Apoſtles rule, who are ſo indifferent in theſe indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t matters, that they wil not in anie caſe yeeld vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the authoritie of their ſuperiours herein? Wherein (I pray you) conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth their obedience? wherein their charitie? wherein ſeeke they the ediſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Church, in procuring and ſeeking the good of others? Forſooth in this, in maintaining that doctrine which formerly they haue taught, in diſobeying authoritie in theſe matters of indifferencie. Yea but what if they ought not to haue taught it, for who is he that ought to teach the doctrine of diſobedience? And ſurely if the Prince directed &amp; aduiſed by the learned and graueſt men, and men in authoritie in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15935:44"/> his realme, hath not power in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to commaund all the Miniſters in his land to keepe a decent and comely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in their miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rie, I knowe not wherein his ſupremacie doth conſiſt: Let euery man, I meane euery Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, be Pope in his own Pariſh. But yet <hi>conſtantiâ cauſae,</hi> they moſt goe on where they haue begun. This were wel if there were <hi>cauſa conſtantiae,</hi> conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the cauſe where there is cauſe of conſtancie is good. But tell me, I pray you, what cauſe of conſtancie where the cauſe was neuer good, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore neuer good for conſtancie, which as it is alwayes good, ſo muſt it alwayes haue a good cauſe: for <hi>error in principio</hi> an error in the beginning, groweth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes to be an hereſie in the ende. My aduice herein I refer vnto the next point, which is the ſecond combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The duties of the equal to his equal be <hi>auxilium</hi> and <hi>conſilium,</hi> counſell and helpe: if thy neighbor that is thy equall
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15935:44"/> be diſtreſſed, and thy helpe may in any matter releeue him and ſtand him in ſtead, thou art bound by Chriſtian du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to put too thy helping hand: if at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie time he erre and be deceiued, the ſame dutie bindeth thee to counſell him. The beſt counſell and helpe that I can giue vnto my brethren, as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the caſes now in hand, which alſo I promiſed in the former point, is this, <hi>poenitentia nunquam ſera, ſi ſeria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third and laſt relation is, of the ſuperiour to the inferiour; and the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thereof be <hi>cuſtodia</hi> and <hi>diſciplina,</hi> cuſtodie and diſcipline, the inferiours are the charge of the ſuperiours, &amp; they ought both to keepe them from harme by cuſtodie, and in order by diſcipline. The Magiſtrates dutie is, to preſerue the innocent people from the iniurie of the oppreſſor, &amp; to puniſh the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by the rod of diſcipline: and ſo the Miniſter is to keepe his flocke from ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening wolues, and ſeparate the ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed ſheepe from the ſound by the rod
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15935:45"/> of diſcipline, and ſo in all others. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of which two duties, of keeping and ordering of the people, the word of God reſembleth a good king vnto a diligent paſtor or ſhepheard, and a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Prince vnto a neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhepheard, 1. <hi>King. 22. 17. Then he ſaid, I ſaw all Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell ſcattered vpon the mountaines, as ſheepe that had no ſhepheard: &amp; the Lord ſaid, theſe haue no maiſter, let euery man returne to his houſe in peace.</hi> Where the people are kept, that is, duly fed and kept in order, that is, diſciplined aright, there be both ſheepe and ſhepheard: but where they be either not at all, or not in order kept, there be ſheep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſhepheard. From hence blinde <hi>Homer</hi> borrowed ſome light, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſee ſomwhat, whoſe king and chiefe magiſtrate is entituled and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſhepheard of the people, whoſe fold is cuſtody &amp; whoſe dog is diſcipline.</p>
               <p>Now if ſome man ſhall ſay, that he is ſo baſe that he hath no inferiour, to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15935:45"/> him I anſwer plainly, there is no man ſo baſe but he hath an inferiour, if not amongſt others, yet in himſelfe: firſt in the whole man, the bodie is infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the ſoule, and the godly haue performed in themſelues theſe duties to their bodies: <hi>Set a watch, ô Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 141</note> 
                  <hi>my mouth,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid;</hi> there is cuſtodie. And in another place <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>I tame my body and bring it into ſubiection,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Paul 1. Cor.</hi> 9. 27. there is diſcipline. Againe in the ſoule, the vnreaſonable part is inferiour to the reaſonable, the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions vnto reaſon: and therefore the Preacher ſpeaking of the hart, the ſeate of affections, giueth vs this counſell, <hi>Omni cuſtodia cuſtodi cor tuum, Looke to thy heart,</hi> and the affections therof <hi>with all diligence,</hi> let reaſon rule them. And euen in reaſon, in the vnderſtanding and will of man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nature, corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ought to be ſubiect to grace. For that we may <hi>inſtare in propoſito,</hi> to ſeeke our owne, and to neglect anothers
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:15935:46"/> wealth, is the part of a carnall and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man, although he be well inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the knowledge of truth. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe to ſeeke anothers good more then our owne pleaſure or profite, is the property of a man indued with the ſpirit of Chriſt, and true charitie. God for his infinite mercie graunt that his grace may rectifie our reaſon, our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may reforme our affections, and our reformed affections may ſo go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne our bodies, that we may grow vp into perfect men in Chriſt leſus: to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with thee ô Father, and thy holy Ghoſt, be all honor, glory, thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing and praiſe, now and for euer. </p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:15935:46"/>
            <head>THE PLAINE foot-path to the pará<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of God.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Matth. 21. 5.</bibl>
               <q>Ecce, rex tuus venit tibi manſuetus. Behold thy king cometh vnto thee meeke.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR Sauiour Chriſt coming into the world, alwayes and at all times loued pouertie and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie: as in his birth, in his life, in his death, &amp; after his death. In his birth, for he had an humble and poore mother; in his life, for he had poore companions and fellowes: in his death, for he had a ſtraite bed, to wit, his croſſe, which was ſo narrowe and ſtraite, that it affoorded not place
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15935:47"/> for both his feete, but that the one was faine to be nailed vpon the other: after his death, for he had a poore ſepulcher, for he was not layd in his owne ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher but in another mans. And yet for all this we ought not to think the more baſely of him, but rather the more highly to eſteeme him: becauſe as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Humilitas virtutum eſt ſublimitas,</hi> humilitie is the height of all vertues: and therefore our Sauiour Chriſt, though he was <hi>humilis,</hi> yet is he not <hi>vilis,</hi> though humble, yet not baſe. As alſo this place enforceth to vs, <hi>manſuetus,</hi> he was <hi>meeke,</hi> there is humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie: <hi>Rex tuus, thy king,</hi> there is ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie. <hi>Rex tuus, thy king,</hi> there is the height of his eſtate: <hi>Manſuetus, meeke,</hi> there is the lowlineſſe of his heart. And theſe two be two parts of this text: the height of his eſtate, and the lowlineſſe of his heart. And the third part is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene theſe two, and is the vſe and application of both theſe vnto vs. <hi>Venit tibi, commeth to thee,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15935:47"/> ſpeaking to the Church, the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the faithfull. Say he is a king, that is his glorie: ſay he is meeke, that is his vertue: but ſay as he ſaith here; that he is thy king, and cometh vnto thee meeke, and that is thy comfort. Is he a king? then is he to be feated. Is he meeke? then is he to be loued. Is he thy king &amp; cometh vnto thee meeke? then is he to be reuerenced, that is, both to be feared and to be loued of thee. Theſe be the parts: of theſe in their order.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the height of his eſtate; <hi>Rex tuus, thy king:</hi> but here me thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth I miſſe a word not ſpoken of in my diuiſion. <hi>Ecce, Behold:</hi> behold thy king. It is true indeed: but yet we did not forget it neither: for it belongeth to the height of his eſtate. For as we ſee high ſtates, great perſonages haue their gentlemen-vſhers go before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make them way: ſo before <hi>Rex tuus, thy king,</hi> goeth <hi>Ecce,</hi> behold thy king cometh; to prepare way for this high
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15935:48"/> eſtate in the harts of men, whither this king meaneth to come: ſo that this <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,</hi> in this place, as it is in moſt other places, is the gentleman vſher word, preparing way in the heart, for greater matter following. So that, as when ſo euer you ſee any gentleman-vſher, you know that he is ſome great perſonage that cometh next: ſo when ſo euer you ſee this word <hi>Ecce, Behold,</hi> you may be ſure that it is ſome great matter that followeth next after it. And as this <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cc,</hi> is a preparatiue word, ſo is it in this place a peaceable word. For <hi>Behold</hi> in this place is as much as be bold: for he is not a traitor, but he is a king: and not a ſtrange king, who perhaps is now in league with thee, but may hereafter do thee a diſpleaſure, if now he ſee where thou art weakeſt; but he is <hi>Rex tuus ô Sion, that will build vp the breaches of Sion, and repaire the decayed places of Hicruſalem:</hi> he it is that cometh, and therefore <hi>Ecce, Behold,</hi> that is, be bold to let him enter in. <hi>Attollite portas, Liſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:15935:48"/> vp the gates,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> in the Pſal. <hi>&amp; introibit rex gloriae, and the king of glorie ſhall come in: Ecce,</hi> behold, ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior here in the Goſpell, <hi>Behold,</hi> that is, be bold to lift vp the gates of thy heart: <hi>venit rex tuus tibi: thy king cometh vnto thee:</hi> ſo that this <hi>Ecce, behold,</hi> hath a double office, outwardly and inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Outwardly, to prepare the cares, which be the firſt gates, that Chriſt by the preaching of the word paſſeth tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough to come into our hearts: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it hath an office inwardly, and that againe is of two ſorts: to prepare the vnderſtanding to know his greatneſſe, that he may be reuerently receiucd, becauſe he is a king: and againe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the will to be willing to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his kindnes, that he may be moſt louingly entertained and embraced, becauſe he is thy king, but ſo that as his kindnes in that he would be ours, ſaith, Behold, I do not dlſdaine: ſo his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in that he is a king, ſaith, Behold, doe not you preſume: Behold, his
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15935:49"/> goodneſſe ſaith he is thine, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be bold: Behold, his greatneſſe ſaith he is a king, and therefore be not too bold. Greatneſſe and goodneſſe begot this child of admiration, <hi>Ecce, Behold: Behold, thy king.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now leauing theſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, let vs come to the ſubſtance of the text; wherein firſt we muſt conſider what manner of king this is, and how it cometh to paſſe that he is ours. <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine Martyr</hi> taxeth the Iewes as groſſe headed, and earthly minded, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding all the promiſes of the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias to be meant viſibly and groſly of ſome great worldly Prince, mightie potentate, or glorious captaine and warrior, who ſhould ſubdue all natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and bring them in ſubiection vnto the Iewes: when as the might, power and authoritie he vſed at his firſt comming was ſaith he <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a ſecret ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and power, not pompous, plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or viſible to the eyes of the world: and this he proueth to be paralleled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15935:49"/> in the deſtruction of Amelech: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for with a ſecret hand or might God fighteth againſt Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech: ſpiritually Amelech is Satan. You may therefore vnderſtand, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret vertue of God was in Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified: whom the diuels do tremble at, and all principalities and powers in the world do feare. And this power of God in Chriſt, as without all ſhew of pompe it did, and doth worke the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of our enemies; ſo in like ſort ſecretly and couertly doth it work our ſaluation by ruling vs inwardly, not with glorious ſhewes, but with his truth. There is indeed a ſpecious and flouriſhing kind of gouernment ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God, which is <hi>regnum inter nos,</hi> the kingdome that is amongſt vs: but that whether it be ciuill authoritie is diſclaimed by our Sauiour in the caſe of the two brethren: no not <hi>Iudex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nos,</hi> not ſo much as a Iudge, much leſſe <hi>Rex inter nos,</hi> a king among vs. Or elſe Eccleſiaſticall, in his ſubiection to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15935:50"/> the high Prieſts authoritie is not ſtood vpon; and yet <hi>Rex,</hi> yet was he a King by the teſtimonie of the heathen, both wiſe men, <hi>vbi eſt ille, qui natus eſt rex Iudaeorum? where is he that is borne king of the Iewes?</hi> and mightie: <hi>Ieſus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth the king of the Iewes.</hi> This king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome therfore being not in ſight, muſt needs be that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that ſecret<note place="margin">Luke 18.</note> power, not <hi>regnum inter nos,</hi> but <hi>intra nos:</hi> not the kingdome that is amongſt vs, but which is within vs. And this as it is, with leſſe noiſe and ſhew, ſo is it with greater maieſtie and power then that other. All the authoritie of the kings in the world, let them trie the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt they can do, either by threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings or promiſes, loue or feare, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not plucke one of theſe ſubiects from God, or remoue a true Chriſtian from Chriſt: witneſſe <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in the priſon, <hi>Ieremie</hi> in the dungeon, the three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the fornace, <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s denne; and all the Apoſtles, <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in wil, the reſt in deed: &amp; infinit Martyrs
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15935:50"/> in the primitiue Church euen in death it ſelf. <hi>T ertullian</hi> ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this point againſt the heathen; <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d againſt the Iewes, but <hi>S. Paule</hi> is verie maruellous in this caſe againſt all the world. <hi>Rom. 8. 38. 39 For I am perſwaded</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther death, nor life, nor Angels, nor prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate vs from the loue of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord:</hi> Take the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars and know the reaſons, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 17. For the kingdome of God is not meat nor drinke, but righteouſneſſe and peace and ioy in the holy Ghoſt; theſe be they that vphold the kingdome of Chriſt in vs, not meate and drinke: for the Apoſtles rule is ſurely true: <hi>meates</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>for the bellie, and the bellie for the meats, but God ſhall deſtroy both it and them:</hi> howbeit, the kingdome of God, and the good that there is neuer ſhal decay. Indeed all other kingdomes without,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:15935:51"/> beſides, or contrarie to Chriſt; take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way theſe things from them, let them haue no meate and drinke, and they will ſoone come to nothing: but the kingdome of God, when all meate, all men, all the world, and all the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes in the world, are ouerthrowne and conſumed, then ſhall it flouriſh in the perfect beautie: for righteouſnes, peace, ioy in the holy Ghoſt, and ſuch like ſpirituall fruites of the kingdome of Chriſt, they be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as <hi>Iuſtine Martyr</hi> ſpeaketh. This then is the firſt point in this king to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, the manner of his kingdome. Hereunto are to be added three other: to the manner of the kingdom, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his ſubiects, the coronation of the king, the glorie of all, both of king, kingdome, and ſubiects, is to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed. For the nature of the ſubiects, vnderſtand that the two kinds of king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, <hi>internos,</hi> and <hi>intranos,</hi> haue two kinds of ſubiects, deliuered vnder two ſimilitudes, of two kind of ſonnes
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15935:51"/> in two promiſes vnto the patriarkes. The one ſimilitude reſembling one kind of ſonnes or ſubiects is deliuered in that promiſe, <hi>as the duſt of the earth: Gen. 13. 16. 1. Sam. 13. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as the ſand on the ſea which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable.</hi> The ſand on the ſea ſide ſaith <hi>Iuſtine Martyr,</hi> as it is innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, ſo is it vnprofitable and vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full too, for no fruite groweth theron: this innumerable &amp; vnprofitable ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> was the children of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> according to the fleſh: of this ſeed the Phariſes were, and bragged thereof to our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>We are the ſeed of Abraham, Abraham is our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Ioh.</hi> 8. 39. Another kinde of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, children and ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> are deliuered in another promiſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der another ſimilitude, and in another place: <hi>ſicut ſtellae coeli: Gen.</hi> 26. 4. and in the 15. of <hi>Geneſ.</hi> he willeth <hi>Abraham to looke vp to heauen, and to tell the ſtarres if he could, and ſaith: ſic erit ſemen tuum.</hi> And theſe are the ſeed, children, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15935:52"/> ſubiects which our Sauior Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſpeaketh of, when he reiecteth the Phariſes as the baſtard brood of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham: If you were the ſonnes of Abraham, you would do the worke of Abraham: Ioh. 8. 39. 40. 41. Stellae coeli,</hi> the ſtarres of<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 4.</note> heauen ſaith the promiſe: the ſonnes or citizens of heauen ſaith the practiſe. <hi>Noſtra conuerſatio eſt in coelis, Our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation is in heauen,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Paule Phil.</hi> 3. 20. Theſe be the attendants, and this is the attendance that this king requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: not the duſt of the earth, for they were the Phariſes: but the ſtars of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, for they be the faithfull; and yet both the ſeed of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next point that cometh in and offereth it ſelfe to be conſidered in this place, is the coronation of this great king: wherein a principall matter (as you know in euerie coronation it is materiall) is, <hi>vnctio,</hi> the annointing of the king: this annointing is deſcribed vnto vs in the 45. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> verſe 7. firſt in the author and act of annointing:
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15935:52"/> 
               <hi>becauſe God euen thy God hath annointed thee:</hi> and ſecondly in the qualitie of the oile; <hi>with the oile of gladneſſe:</hi> and thirdly in the quantitie thereof: <hi>aboue thy fellowes.</hi> In all which points is poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out vnto vs nothing elſe but the ſpirituall annointing of Chriſt with grace, which is there called the oile of gladneſſe: and that the oile of gladnes is grace, and ſignifieth grace in that place, it is plaine by the effect which is ſet downe in the firſt wordes of that verſe, to be <hi>the loue of righteouſneſſe, and hatred of wickedneſſe;</hi> and all this is the worke of grace. And that Chriſt was and is annointed with this ſpirituall oile, the ſpeciall grace of God, that is plaine both by his conception, <hi>Luke 1. 35. The holy Ghoſt ſhall come vpon thee, and the power of the moſt higheſt ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſhadow thee:</hi> and alſo by his life, <hi>Luk. 2. 40. And the child grew, and waxed ſtrong in ſpirit, and was filled with wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the grace of God was with him.</hi> And further that hee was annointed
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15935:53"/> with ſpirituall oile, the ſpeciall grace of God <hi>aboue his fellowes,</hi> that is eaſily declared in three points. The firſt grace of God, that Chriſt had aboue all his fellowes, all the children of God, is <hi>gratia capitis,</hi> he hath grace to be the head, whereof the whole Church is the bodie: <hi>Epheſ. 5. 23. Col.</hi> 2. 19. The ſecond grace th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Chriſt hath aboue all his fellowes, is <hi>gratia originalis tuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> the grace of originall righteouſnes: we all are conceiued and borne in ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſinne, but he without ſinne, in originall holineſſe and righteouſneſſe; and therefore he is called in the firſt of <hi>S. Luke</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that holy thing which ſhall be borne of thee,</hi> borne holy, and doth liue holy for euer: in which ſence he is called by <hi>Dauid: Deus iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, the God of righteouſneſſe:</hi> &amp; of <hi>Paule</hi> is he ſaid to be, <hi>Homo iuſtitiae, 1. Cor. 1. 30. who of God is made vnto vs wiſdom, righteouſneſſe, and ſanctification and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi> The third wherein Chriſt ſurpaſſeth all his fellowes, all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:15935:53"/> who through his grace are made alſo the children of God, is <hi>gratia hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaticae vnionis,</hi> the grace of his hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaticall vnion, whereby God and man are made one Chriſt, hauing vnited in one perſon the two in ſome reſpect, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe contrarie natures of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and the manhood. <hi>Phil. 2. 6. 7. Gratiâ capitis,</hi> in the grace of the head, <hi>gratiâ originalis iuſtitiae,</hi> in the grace of originall iuſtice, and <hi>gratiâ hypoſtaticae vnionis,</hi> in the grace of hypoſtaticall v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: in theſe three annointings, in theſe three graces, Chriſt excelleth all Chriſtians; and all kings, Chriſtians and others. And the reuerſion of theſe three graces, and the ouerplus of theſe three ointments of Chriſt addeth or implieth three eſſentiall points in the office of all kings. Firſt as Chriſt is the head of the Church, ſo vnder God the king is ſupreme head of his kingdome in all cauſes. Secondly, as Chriſt hath originall iuſtice, ſo all the offices of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, all the miniſters of iuſtice, and all
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:15935:54"/> the acts of iuſtice in the whole realme, be originally in the king, and come o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally from the king. Thirdly, as in the perſon of Chriſt both the natures be vnited: ſo in the office of the king both eſtates be combined, and he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being the Lieutenant of God in his office, after a ſort may iuſtly be ſaid to be ioyned vnto God. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing that is done at the corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this king, is the proclamation, or title proclaimed: and that is not <hi>Rex Franciae,</hi> the king of France, nor <hi>Rex Aſiae,</hi> the king of Aſia, nor <hi>Rex terrae,</hi> the king of the whole earth: but <hi>Rex magnus ſuper omnes Deos, a great king a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all Gods: Pſal. 95. 3. Rex regum, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus dominantium, that is bleſſed and Prince onely king of kings, and Lord of Lords. 1. Tim.</hi> 6. 15. Nay, when he is crowned, the trumpets of heauen, nay the Angels of God, nay the Spirit of God giueth him this title, <hi>Rex gloriae, the king of glorie,</hi> and <hi>Dominus exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum, the Lord of hoſts: Pſal.</hi> 25. There
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15935:54"/> be two gifts of God which in a ſumme or in an epitome do ſet downe vnto vs all God his gifts: the one is the gift of God his grace, the other of his glorie. Grace is preſent at the coronation of Chriſt our king, but glory is the crown it ſelfe which laſteth for euer. Now if anie deſire to know this and to ſee this, he deſireth an excellent thing: but let him not be too buſie for ſeare his eyes be dazled, &amp; for feare of preſumption, and ſo of confuſion. One there is that ſeemeth to ſet downe twelue things or marks whereby the greatneſſe of the glorie of the Saints in ſome ſort may be vnderſtood, but we will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our owne weakeneſſe, ſhallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and vnworthineſſe, and not ſeeke to be wiſer, or ſeeme to ſee more then the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> (though caught vp into the third heauen) could euer at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto: for he confeſſeth, <hi>the things which eye hath not ſeene, neither eare hath heard, neither came into mans hart, are, which God hath prepared for them
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15935:55"/> that loue him.</hi> And if for all them that loue him theſe incomparable good things be prepared, then how much more for his owne only begotten Son, in whom he is well pleaſed, be theſe infinite, incomprehenſible, glorious, good things, not prepared onely, but alſo powred out vpon: and this in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, though what they be, our ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low braine and weake capacity cannot comprehend, is the crowne of glorie fitted to the king of glorie, and by him beſtowed likewiſe vpon the veſſels of gloric. <hi>Iuſtine Martyr,</hi> rather telling what it is not then what it is, in fower priuatiue words, doth, as neare as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſet out this crowne of glorie, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the firſt depriueth vs of paſſion, the ſcond of corruption, the third of ſorow, &amp; the fourth of mortalitie. For this letter <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a priuatiue in euery one of theſe words, but yet a priuatiue of our priuations, which is an excellent infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite good thing, we being infinite euill
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15935:55"/> and corrupt, to be depriued of all our priuations, and to be refined from all our corruption, is an vnualuable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite and bleſſing of almighty God: and not onely this our euill ſhall be taken from vs, but alſo this, his goods ſhall be beſtowed and conferred vpon vs: and this is that, that inferreth the next point, in the next word: <hi>Tuus, thine:</hi> that appropriateth this king vnto vs, to euerie one in particular: <hi>Rex tuus:</hi> thy king: for what was ſaid to Sion, as to the whole Church, that is ſaid to euery citizen of Sion, euery member of the Church in particular.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Eccerex tuus: Behold thy king.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>We are his, and therfore he is ours: he our God, we his creatures; he our redeemer, we his redeemed; he our Lord, we his ſeruants; he our king, we his ſubiects. <hi>Quod ſumus,</hi> that we are, we are of him: <hi>Quod ſumus filij,</hi> in that we are ſonnes, we are it in him. If thou haſt anie grace it is his gift; if thou haſt any goodneſſe, it is his grace. <hi>Nam de
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:15935:56"/> plenitudine eius omnes bibimus,</hi> for of his fulneſſe we all haue drunke. What then? is his fulnes euer a whit the emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier becauſe all haue drunke thereof? not at all: for in him is <hi>plenitudo ſontis,</hi> the fulneſſe of the fountain, in vs there is <hi>plenitudo v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſis,</hi> the fulneſſe of a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell: and therefore according as in other, nay infinitely aboue the nature and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of all other fountains: though all the veſſels be filled with grace from the fountaine, yet is the fountaine of grace neuer a whit the emptier. Thus haſt thou poſſeſſion in him, and yet he full of power in himſelfe notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: thus hath he beſtowed a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite vpon thee in that he is thine, and thou doeſt owe a dutie vnto him, in that he is thy king, which requireth thy obedience, and that in ſuch ſort as he is thy king. To him that is the king of our countrey, we muſt do ſuch ſeruice as our countrey lawes commaund vs: to him that is our ſpirituall king, we
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15935:56"/> owe ſpirituall obedience: and to him that is our heauenly king, we muſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tie that is required of all thoſe that ſhall be made citizens of the kingdome of heauen: that is, inwardly to ſerue God in ſpirit and in truth. Yea but he ſpeaketh but to Sion onely, Tell the daughter Sion, Behold, thy king; and therefore it ſeemeth that none but the Iewes had this intereſt in him. Yea but this title was written ouer his head at his death, <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth king of the Iewes,</hi> in three languages. Hebrew, Greeke and Latine, to ſignifie, that as well Grecians, and Romaines, or anie nation elſe that truſteth in his name, haue this intereſt in him as well as the Iewes, that he will be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir king: <hi>For he is not a Iewe that is one outward, neither is that circumciſion that is outwardly in the fleſh, but he is a Iew that is one within, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>that is circumciſion that is inwardly in the heart,</hi> as the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. Yea, but how could any haue this intereſt in him ſeeing he is God? To
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15935:57"/> this a certaine auncient diuine anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that, <hi>fuit in eo ſublimit as diuina, cum infirmitate humana,</hi> diuine excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, with humane infirmitie: he is <hi>Rex,</hi> the king, in that he is the great God: he is <hi>tuus,</hi> thine, in that he was made weake man.</p>
               <p>Whereby we may ſee, that we may prepare the way to the next point, how farre Chriſt humbled himſelfe, that he might be ours. Belowe the nature of God is the nature of Angels, belowe the nature of Angels is the nature of man, below the nature of man is the puniſhment due to mans nature per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and depraued. Firſt therefore Chriſt humbled himſelfe below him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, below his diuine nature, in that he was made leſſe then himſelf: <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. againe he humbled himſelf below the Angels in that he could ſuffer, which the Angels can not: and therefore it is ſaid in another place, <hi>Minuiſti cum pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo minus Angelis: Thou haſt made him a litle lower then the Angels.</hi> Thirdly he
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:15935:57"/> deſcended lower then the nature of man, in that he was a reproach among men, <hi>vermis ſum &amp; non homo, I am a</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 22</note> 
                  <hi>worme and not a man: Eſa. 53. 2. Non eſt ei ſpecies neque decor: He hath neither forme nor beauty.</hi> Fourthly he humbled him ſelfe euen vnto puniſhment. Now there be three degrees of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: there is <hi>poena valdè ignominioſa,</hi> a verie ſhamefull death, as that of hanging, which belongeth to malefactors, there is <hi>poena valdè laborioſa,</hi> a verie painfull death, as to be fleyed, as was <hi>S. Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomew,</hi> or to be broiled, as was <hi>S. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence:</hi> and there is <hi>poena,</hi> a puniſhment, that is both theſe, both verie ſhamefull and verie painfull, and this is the death of the croſſe, both ſhamefull as being the death of theeues, painfull as tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in the moſt neruous and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiue partes. Wilt thou now trie thy ſtate in him, and ſee his eſtate in him ſelfe: then muſt thou aſcend vnto him by the ſame ſteppes or degrees by the which he hath deſcended vnto thee;
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:15935:58"/> he is thy puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t remoued becauſe he bare the puniſhment due vnto thee; he is thy man, in that he was made man for thee; he is thy Angell, in that he is the meſſenger of God for thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation; he is thy God, in that he made thee; he is thy king, in that he is thy God: thy puniſhment, thy man, thy Angell, thy God, thy king. Thy pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, to free thee from paine, thy man to ſhield thee from ſhame, thy Angell to bring thee vnto God, thy God to guide thee with his grace, thy king to giue thee of his glorie. And thus much of the firſt point, which is the height of his eſtate; now followeth the ſecond, which is the lowlineſſe of his heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Manſuetus, meeke.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>This is the verie receptacle and veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell whereinto God vſeth to powre all his graces: <hi>Humilibus dat gratiam, God giueth grace to the humble: Iam. 4. Sicut enim aqua ad loca ima, ita gratia ad cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da humilia currit,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> as
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15935:58"/> the water runneth to the lower places, ſo grace floweth to the lowly heart. And in his tenth booke <hi>De verbis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Marie Magdalene,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Quanto humiliùs ſedebat, tanto ampliùs capiebat,</hi> the lower that ſhe ſate, the more was her receipt of grace: at our Sauiours feete ſhe receiued more grace then in the kings throne. <hi>Iacob,</hi> when hee was loweſt, euen on the ground; and when he was weakeſt, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen diſarmed of al his ſenſes by ſleepe: then was he greateſt in Gods fauour, for then he ſaw a ladder reaching from heauen to earth, &amp; the Angels deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and aſcending the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>upon, <hi>Gen. 28. Confluit aqua ad humilitatis conuallem,</hi> the water floweth to the lowly vallies; and therefore high places are drie whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> low are full of water: light things of no worth, as feathers, mount with the wind; but things that haue ſubſtance and be of value, as gold, lye ſtill below on the ground. The beſt eares of corne bow downe their heads, but they that
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:15935:59"/> haue nothing in them ſtand ſtarting and ſtaring bolt vpright: and the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſey amongſt men, that braggeth of himſelfe, is of leſſer eſtimation with Chriſt, then the Publican that beateth his breaſt. <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> in his Paſtorals, ſaith, that <hi>pupilla oculi nigra videt, albu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginem tollerans non videt,</hi> the apple of the eye that ſeemeth blacke, doth ſee; but that which hath a white filme ouer it, that hath a pearle in it, ſeeth not: ſo is it with the eye of the ſoule, as it is with the eye of the bodie: that minde that ſeemeth blacke in it owne ſight, that ſeemeth darke, vile and vglie of it ſelfe to it ſelfe, that mind ſeeth it ſelfe: if thy vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding naturally ſeemeth darke vnto thee, thy wil deformed, thy affections vile and baſe, and thy whole naturall man vglie and corrupt in thy ſight, then is the ball of thine eye black, then ſeeſt thou. But if all ſeeme plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, faire and goodly, and nothing in thy ſight is amiſſe, then haſt thou a white filme drawne ouer thine eye,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:15935:59"/> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haſt thou a pearle in thine eye, and this precious eye with a pearle in it ſeeth not at all, neither it ſelfe nor anie thing elſe, as it is in deed, &amp; as it ought to ſee it. And therefore <hi>Ptolomie</hi> well ſaith, that <hi>inter ſapientes, ſapientior qui humilior,</hi> amongſt wiſe men, he is the wiſer that is the humbler: and the wiſe man ſaith: <hi>Pro. 11. Vbi humilitas ibi ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia, Where there is humilitie there is wiſedome.</hi> Scalpon the Philoſopher wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to <hi>Alexander</hi> hath theſe words, <hi>Praeſto eſt Deus tibi dare ſapientiam:</hi> God indeed (ſaith he) is readie to giue thee wiſedome, <hi>ſed non habes vbiteneas eam, cum ſuperbia plenus ſis:</hi> but thou haſt not wherein to put it, ſeeing thou art full of pride. And therefore <hi>Iſidore</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Deſcende vt aſcendas,</hi> deſcend that thou mayeſt aſcend; be humbled that thou mayeſt be exalted: for he that extolleth himſelfe ſhall be abaſed, and he that exalteth himſelfe ſhall be brought low. And here I pray you marke three degrees or ſteps of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie:
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15935:60"/> the firſt is <hi>ſubdere ſe maiori, nec praeferre ſe equali:</hi> to ſubmit our ſelues vnto our betters, and not to preferre our ſelues before our equals, <hi>&amp; iſle,</hi> and this is neceſſarie to ſaluation. The ſecond is <hi>ſubdere ſe aequali<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nec ſe praeferre minori:</hi> a man to ſubmit himſelfe to his equall, and not to preferre himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his inferiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, <hi>&amp; iſle,</hi> and this is <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundans,</hi> this aboundeth. The third is yet one d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gree further: <hi>ſubdere ſe mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, in quo eſi omnis iuſtitia;</hi> to ſubmit himſelfe to his inſeriour, wherein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth ail iuſtice. But to come ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more neare to this point that we haue in hand: other do otherwiſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the works of humilitie, into theſe ſoure ſteps or degrees. The firſt is <hi>ſpernere mundum,</hi> to deſpiſe the world; this is the firſt ſtep to humilitie: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>ſpernere nullum,</hi> to deſpiſe no man: the third is, <hi>ſpernere ſeipſum,</hi> but to thinke baſely of himſelfe: the fourth is, <hi>non ſpernere ſeipſum ſperni,</hi> not to ſcorne that he is ſcorned, not to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:15935:60"/> that he himſelfe is deſpiſed: and this indeede is the proper worke of meekeneſſe, which is defined by the auncient diuines: <hi>Tranquilitas animi nullis moleſtus irritati,</hi> Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kneſſe is the quietneſſe of a mind, that can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked by no troubles to diſquietneſſe; and this is <hi>non ſpernere ſeipſum ſperni:</hi> not to ſcorne that he himſelfe is ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: for many can beare other trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, as pouertie, ſickneſſe, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment patiently, and ſome can beare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches and not reuile againe; but he that can be contented to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned and ſcorned in this world, he that ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not this, he ſure is built vpon a ſure rocke, he hath that quietneſſe of mind that can not be diſquieted; he is meeke: and ſuch was this king, that deſpiſed not when he was deſpiſed: nay he came into the world that he might be ſcorned: and yet being a king he did not deſtroy, but purchaſed a pardon with his owne heart bloud, euen for thoſe that ſcorned him. And ſuch ſhall we be, if we hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble our ſelues
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15935:61"/> vnder his hand that humbled himſelfe for vs, euen vnto the death, and that the death of the croſſe for vs: <hi>Phil. 2. 8. Manſueti dicuntur quaſi manu aſſueti:</hi> They are ſaid to be meek ſaith the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, that are brought vp by the hand: and therefore repentant ſinners are ſaid to be meeke, who leauing their fierceneſſe and naughtineſſe, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to come vnto the hands of the Lord of mercie.</p>
               <p>Now there be two wayes whereby ſinners are made meeke. For <hi>Albertus</hi> ſaith, that there be ſome beaſts &amp; birds as Faulcons and ſuch like, which are made tame, and returne to the hand of their maiſter, when they perceiue and feele ſome benefit, receiue ſome meate from the hand of him that called them: and ſo Chriſt, willing to conuert ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners vnto himſelfe, leaueth not off to offer his benefites vnto them, and to feede them with his owne fleſh and bloud; and thus he cometh meeke. But there be ſome that will not be made
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15935:61"/> meeke or tame, but by blowes, by whips and puniſhments: For the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher ſaith, <hi>lib. 8. de animalibus,</hi> that the Elephant being taken is beaten of his rider, that he may obey him, and thus they do tame him; his two former feete are tied hard together vntill ſuch time as he becometh tame, and quiet; and then euer after he becometh as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient and familiar as anie dog. Now then beloued, if we be of the nature of Elephants, ſtubburne and proud, and will not be tamed but by blowes, ſo that God to tame vs is euen driuen as it were, to ſend famine, the ſword, and peſtilence: the fault is not therefore in God, for he is meeke; but the fault is in our ſelues, for we would not regard him when he ſent vs his benefiets, of peace, plentie, &amp; health, neither would we be made tame or become meeke thereby. If therefore now in ſtead of peace he ſhall giue vs warre, in ſtead of plentie he ſhall ſend a famine, and in ſtead of health ſuch ſickneſſes and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:15935:62"/> as haue not bene heard of in anie ages: yet is he no changeling, but we will not be chaunged: O that yet ye would repent and returne vnto him, and you ſhall trie him, euen yet alſo to be meeke and gentle, to forgiue you all your ſinnes, and to receiue you into fauour: and thus much of the ſecond part, the lowlineſſe of his heart.</p>
               <p>Now followeth the third part, which is the vſe and application of both the other, and therefore is placed in the midſt betweene them both.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Venit tibi: Cometh vnto thee.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>If he be a king, and be not our king, what is that to vs? If he be our king, and be not meeke, what comfort is that to vs? If he be a king, our king, and meeke; and yet come not vnto vs, what bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite haue we by all this? And therefore this <hi>venit tibi,</hi> cometh vnto thee is the vſe of all: for this cauſeth both our king and his meekneſſe to be good vnto vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Venit tibi: Cometh vnto thee.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>That is, <hi>ad vtilitatem tuam,</hi> for thy
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:15935:62"/> profite, he cometh to thee: for thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, to ſuffer death for thee. See here the exceeding loue of our Sauior, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with our infinite profite: <hi>Greater loue hath no man then this, that a man ſhould lay downe his life for his friends: Iohn.</hi> 15. For whereas there be foure ſignes to manifeſt our loue by, the laſt and greateſt of all is this, as you ſhall ſee by their ſeuerall examples. Firſt loue is made manifeſt by words, as by ſignes; for when the heart is full of loue, then the mouth is ful of words of loue: <hi>Luk. 6. Ex abundantia cordis os loquitur, Of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh.</hi> Secondly loue is made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by benefites beſtowed, and this is greater then the firſt: for manie will ſpeake good words and full of loue, which will not performe the like in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And therefore <hi>S. Gregori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſaith: <hi>Probatio dilectionis exhibitio eſt operis,</hi> the proofe of a mans good will is the beſtowing of a good turne. Thirdly loue is made manifeſt by perſonal obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:15935:63"/> if anie man for loue in perſon doth ſeruice; and this is greater then the former: for many would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſupply in loue the want of their friends, but not to ſerue in perſon: but <hi>Iacob</hi> ſerued <hi>Laban</hi> ſeauen yeares for <hi>Rahel, Gen.</hi> 19. becauſe he loued her. Fourthly, loue is made manifeſt by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering aduerſitie for the thing loued: <hi>Multi enim darent perſonam ſuam ad ſeruiendum, qui non darent anima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuam ad moriendum;</hi> ſaith one; Many would giue their bodies to ſerue, who neuer will giu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their liues to die for loue: and of this ſigne of this loue, the Apoſtle <hi>Paule,</hi> the true diſciple of Chriſt ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, 2. <hi>Cor. 12. 15. I will moſt gladly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow, and will be beſtowed for you:</hi> but Chriſt the maiſter of <hi>Paule</hi> &amp; all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, he hath ſhewed all theſe ſignes of his loue vnto his ſpouſe, which is his Church. For in the time of the Law and the Prophets, he ſhewed his loue by his words: <hi>Baruch. 4. Beati ſumus Iſrael: We are bleſſed ô Iſrael, becauſe thoſe
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:15935:63"/> things that pleaſe God are manifeſt to vs.</hi> Secondly he ſhewed his loue by his benefites beſtowed, both in the law, before the law, and after the law: he hath giuen vs both temporall, corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and ſpirituall bleſſings, and he hath promiſed vs alſo celeſtial and heauenly benefites: <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. Thirdly he came in perſon and ſerued for vs, not ſeauen yeares, as <hi>Iacob</hi> did, but thirtie yeares; <hi>in forma ſerui,</hi> euen in the forme of a ſeruant: <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 8. But principally in this place his loue is ſet downe, where he is ſaid to come vnto vs, not to dine with vs, but to die for vs, not to ſuppe with vs, but to ſuffer for vs. And what did he come to ſuffer? <hi>Dura verba, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riora verbera, duriſsima crucis tormenta:</hi> He came to ſuffer hard words, harder ſtripes, but the moſt hard and cruell torments of the croſſe. Wherein as he taketh infinite paines, ſo he doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good. For firſt in that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, he muſt of neceſſitie <hi>mouere,</hi> moue towards vs, and <hi>Chriſtus eſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:15935:64"/> mobile Die,</hi> the firſt moueable goods of God; and as Chriſt moueth, ſo moue all the ſpheres of the grace of God, whether ſpirituall or temporall, for our good, according to our Sauior Chriſt his owne ſpeech in the Goſpel: <hi>Primum quaerite regnum Dei, Firſt ſeeke the kingdome of God, and the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, and all other things ſhall be caſt vnto you.</hi> Secondly, in that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto vs, he muſt needs <hi>remouere,</hi> remoue all thoſe things that make a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration betweene him and vs; for <hi>eiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem eſt remouere, cuius eſt mouere,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth vnto the ſame to remoue whoſe propertie it is to moue: as we ſee in the fire, it hath a propertie to moue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and it hath an abilitie to remoue thoſe things that hinder it from mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vpward, as ſtraw, wood, ſtone, or whatſoeuer cometh in the way whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it moueth, by burning it remoueth: and ſo Chriſt coming vnto vs, that he might moue the better vnto vs, he hath remoued and broken downe the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:15935:64"/> wall of ſinne, that made a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betweene him and vs, by dying he hath taken away the ſting of death, and by deſcending into hell, he, the true ſpirituall <hi>Sampſon,</hi> hath broken o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and borne away the gates of hell, that he might come vnto vs. Looke how farre the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo far hath he remoued all euil from thee, by mouing, that is, by comming vnto thee, if thy heart be prepared by faith and repentance to receiue him. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by coming vnto vs, he doth not only <hi>mouere,</hi> moue ouer vs by his protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; nor yet <hi>remouere,</hi> remoue euill from vs by his power: but he doth alſo <hi>promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerè,</hi> promote, &amp; ſet forward the grace of God in vs by his mercy; for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is he called <hi>Rex tuus,</hi> thy king in his iourney towards thee: Behold thy king cometh vnto thee, that like as a king preferreth his ſeruants, ſo Chriſt preferreth all Chriſtians that are truly ſo called; that is, all thoſe that not only in name, but in nature alſo reſemble
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:15935:65"/> Chriſt. It is accounted in the way to preferment, to be admitted to come to the king, and to haue acceſſe vnto him: but if the king vouchſafe to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, thou ſhalt haue worſhip in the ſight of all the people: but if the king will vouchſafe to be thy king, and then come vnto thee, what canſt thou want, that thou ſhalt not haue at his hands; when he himſelfe is thy portion and thy poſſeſſion, and cometh vnto thee as thy poſſeſſion for euermore?</p>
               <closer>Euen ſo Lord Ieſus come quickly. Amen.</closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:15935:65"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
